<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A stronge defence of the maryage of pryestes agaynste the Pope Eustachians, and Tatanites of our time, made dialogue wise by Iohn Veron, betwixte Robin Papyste, and the true Christian.</title>
            <author>Véron, John, d. 1563.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1562</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24687</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106223</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841943</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841943</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6563</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6563)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 582:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A stronge defence of the maryage of pryestes agaynste the Pope Eustachians, and Tatanites of our time, made dialogue wise by Iohn Veron, betwixte Robin Papyste, and the true Christian.</title>
                  <author>Véron, John, d. 1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 65 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fletestrete nere to Sainct Dunstons Churche by Thomas Marshe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1562?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Celibacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6563:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6563:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶A ſtronge <hi>DEFENCE OF THE maryage of Pryeſtes, agaynſte</hi> the Pope <hi>Euſtachians,</hi> and <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanites</hi> of our time, made dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue wiſe by <hi>Iohn Veron,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixte Robin Papyſte, and the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>I. CORIN. VII.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>For auoyding of fornication, let euery man haue his wife, and euerye woman her huſbande.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEBRE. XIII.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>¶Wedlocke is honourable among all, and the bed vndefyled, but whoremongers and adulterers god wyl iudge.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶Imprynted at London in Flete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrete nere to Sainct Dunſtons Churche by Thomas Marſhe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6563:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6563:2"/>
            <head>☞To the worſhypful, Maſter <hi>George Baſford Leather ſealer,</hi> Citezen of London. &amp;c. Iohn Veron wyſheth grace, peace of conſcyence, and encreaſe in all godlynes from God the father, throughe hys Sonne Ieſu Chyrſte oure Lorde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much as many doe yet nowe at thys time, in the whyche it hath pleaſed God our heauenlye father, of hys mere mercye and goodneſſe to viſyte this floryſhynge realme againe, with his holy and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred word and with the goſpel of his ſonne Ieſu Chriſt, kycke againſt the lawful marryage of the faythful mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the church holding ſtil opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that it is not lawfull for them, which are preachers of gods worde, and do minyſter the ſacramentes, to be couppled in Matrimonye:<note place="margin">A briefe ſum of the whole doctrine that is taught in this booke.</note> I haue thought good, ſomewhat to write of this matter, &amp; to proue by manyfeſte ſcriptures, and by the autorytyes of the olde &amp; auncyent wryters, that al
<pb facs="tcp:6563:3"/> they which haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gift of chaſtity may lawfully, &amp; wythout any offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god mary,<note place="margin">Hebre, xiii.</note> yea, although they had by foolyſhe and fonde vowes not commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of god, bound them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to the contrary, that ſo they may auoide fornication with all kynde of vnclenlines, and kepte them ſelues in that holy eſtate, vndefiled members of our ſauiour Ieſu chriſt. Firſt, and foremoſte theſe are the wordes of thapoſtell: Maryage is honourabell amonge all, and the bed vndefyled. Wherby this apoſtel doth admoniſh vs, that as incontinency, is a diſeaſe commen to men of all ſortes, and degrees, ſo maryage beynge the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie againſt it, is offred by the free mercy and goodnes of god, to al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men withoute anye reſpecte,<note place="margin">The mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate vſe of a woman in lawfull Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony is reputed for no ſinne.</note> and that the moderat vſe of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in lawfull Matrimonie, is not repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for ſinne, for which cauſe, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the bedde of the godly maried, vndefiled. Wherunto doth that god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye aunciente father agree, I meane Paphnutius, who in the councel of
<pb facs="tcp:6563:3"/> Nice withſtode thoſe,<note place="margin">Sozo. li. i. ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi. cap. xxiii. Socrate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan. Epipha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus. li. ii. cap. xiiil.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wolde haue forbydden maryage vnto the miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſing wedlocke to be honorabel, and the cohabytaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of man with hys lawfull wyfe to be chaſtity. Againe, this holy Apoſtel in his firſte epiſtel to the Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſaieth plainely thus: let euerye man haue hys wyfe, and let euerye wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man haue her houſbande,<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> for auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Which ſaying, as it ought not to be extended to thoſe, that haue of God, the ſyngular gifte of chaſtitie, ſo it perteineth generally to al them, that wantinge the ſame, haue neede of the remedye, whyche the creatoure of all, knowynge beſt the complexcion and nature of men, did inſtitute and ordeine, ſaing:<note place="margin">Gene, ii.</note> It is not good for man to be alone. And wheras y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemyes, do affirme, that this ought to be vnderſtanded, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of thoſe that be alredie couppled in Matrymonye, that wee ſhoulde graunte that to be true, what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they gather of it, but that the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is alſo geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwere. </seg>
               </label> vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that
<pb facs="tcp:6563:4"/> are vnmaryed? If a man dyd vſe this kynd or that kynd of meate, and the phiſicion ſhuld ſay vnto hym: ſee that ye vſe ſtil that meate, and it ſhal preſerue you from this ſickeneſſe, or that ſicknes that ye are inclinde and geuen to: if any other which vſed not that dyet, and yet felte him ſelfe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte to that dyſeaſe, heard this Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicions counſel, woulde not he yf he tendered his health, thinke that this were ſpoken vnto hym alſo? Euen ſo yf the Apoſtel ſhould ſay, to them, that be alredye maryed: See that ye abyde, and contynew ſtill in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſtate of Matrimony, vſinge with all thankefulnes the remedye that god hathe appoynted for you, and ye ſhal thereby auoyde whoredome and vnclenlynes, and conſequently euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge damnation, whyche is of God prepared for whoremongers, and adulterers: Who beyng vnma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed, and feelynge them ſelues ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte to fornycation (yf at leſte they dyd tender the health and ſaluation of theyr owne ſoules) woulde not
<pb facs="tcp:6563:4"/> thinke this to be ſpoken vnto them? And that they are bounde to vſe the ſame remedy againſt filthines &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane liuinge,<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> that the maried folke are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to vſe? this I am ſure,<note place="margin">That is with the fyer of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence. I meane, when mens will, for lacke of the gifte of chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye doth ſo geue place, to the luſte that tempteth, that he can not call vpon god with a quyete con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> is ſpoken generally to al, that haue not the gift of chaſtity. Let the vnma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ried and widowes, yf they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteine, mary, for it is better to marie then to burne. Againe if thou takeſt a wife thou ſinneſt not: likewyſe if a virgine mary ſhe ſinneth not, neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe ſuche ſhall haue trouble in theyr fleſh. Whereby he vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the troubles and cares of theyr children and family, and other lyke, which do belong vnto the croſſe that god wyl haue to be anexed to this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.<note place="margin">Similitude.</note> And for the which they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute &amp; voide of the gift of continen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie, ought in no wiſe to forbeare wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iocke. For, that were, as yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lng extremely ſicke, ſhold ſay: I haue nede of that Phyſike, but becauſe it is better, I wyll not take it, I had lyeffer dye, than to ſuffer it to come wythin my lyppes: Who would not
<pb facs="tcp:6563:5"/> iudge that man, to be worſe than madde? But this goodly liberty that the holy ghoſt did geue vnto all men by his holy Apoſtel, who ſaieth in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place: I doe not ſpeake thys, to tangle you in a ſnare, is clene ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken awaye by the tirannye of that Antichriſte of Rome, who dyd laye on the neckes of hys cleargie a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, heauier tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mount Aethna as the commune by worde goeth. Wherof,<note place="margin">Aethna is a mountaine in in Scicile that burneth continuallye, and is of the Italians cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led mount Gibello.</note> many dyd very greuouſlie complaine, as it doth manyfeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by theyr owne wrytinges. Theſe are the wordes of Baptiſta Mantuanus beinge a Carmelite, in the life of Hilarius beinge byſhop of Poetiers in Fraunce.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Baptiſta Mantuanus in vita Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larii.</note>Integritas vitae, legum prudentia, cultus</l>
               <l>Caelituum, tutela inopum, diadema pedum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Pictauienſe tibi, dum nil mortalia euras,</l>
               <l>Dum viuis tibi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſorte tua contentus, ah omni</l>
               <l>Ambitione procul, populo applaudente, tulerunt</l>
               <l>Non nocuit tibi progenies, non obſtitit vxor</l>
               <l>Legitimo coniuncta toro, non horruit illa</l>
               <l>Tempeſtate deus thalamos, cunabula, taedas.</l>
               <l>Sola erat in praetio, quae nunc incognita virtus.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:5"/>
               <l>Sordet, et attrito viuit cum plebe cucullo,</l>
               <l>Propterea leges, quaeſunt connubia contra</l>
               <l>Eſſe malas quidem perhibent, prudentia patrum</l>
               <l>Non ſatis aduertit, dicunt, quid ferre recuſet,</l>
               <l>Quid valeat natura pati: Ceruicibus aiunt,</l>
               <l>Hoc inſuaue iugum noſtris imponere Chriſtus</l>
               <l>Noluit: iſtud onus quod adhuc qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plurima mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtra</l>
               <l>Fecit, ab audaci, dicunt pietate repertum.</l>
               <l>Tutius eſſe volunt, qua lex diuina ſinebat</l>
               <l>Iſſe via, vete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſequi veſtigia patrum:</l>
               <l>Quorum vita fuit melior, cum coniuge, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nunc</l>
               <l>Noſtra ſit excluſis thalamis et coniugis vſu.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which verſes, I wyll Englyſhe as wel as I can, folowynge rather the ſenſe and meanyng, then eyther the wordes or the Meter.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The integritye of lyfe,</l>
               <l>And of lawes the ſcience,</l>
               <l>The worſhipping of god,</l>
               <l>And of them the defence,</l>
               <l>Which pore and nedy were,</l>
               <l>While thou liuedſt, not caring</l>
               <l>For worldly pompe and pryde,</l>
               <l>Nor for rycheſſe paſſing,</l>
               <l>But in all thy pilgrimage,</l>
               <l>And life helde the content,</l>
               <l>With that which god appointed,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:6"/>
               <l>And from ambition went,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">By this peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the byſhopryke.</note>Vnto the haue broughte</l>
               <l>Of Poetyers moſt famous</l>
               <l>The myter and croiſſier both,</l>
               <l>Thereat being ioyous</l>
               <l>The people that in it dweld,</l>
               <l>Nor yet did then thy wife</l>
               <l>Vnto the by the lawe ioyned,</l>
               <l>Whych then was ryfe,</l>
               <l>Nor thy lawefull iſſue,</l>
               <l>That by her thou hadſt had,</l>
               <l>Hinder the any whit,</l>
               <l>But that thou waſt lad</l>
               <l>With the charge of the flocke</l>
               <l>Which Chriſt ſo deare had bought,</l>
               <l>For, then god in thoſe dayes,</l>
               <l>As of men well is thought</l>
               <l>Mariage allowed,</l>
               <l>And that to it perteyned:</l>
               <l>For, then vertue alone,</l>
               <l>Whereunto fewe attayned,</l>
               <l>Prayſed and allowed was,</l>
               <l>And had in moſt price,</l>
               <l>Whych nowe vnknowen is,</l>
               <l>And dwelles among lyce,</l>
               <l>Emongeſt them, I meane,</l>
               <l>That in ragges do go,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:6"/>
               <l>And in pouertye liue,</l>
               <l>Miſerye, gryefe, and wo,</l>
               <l>Therfore, thoſe lawes, I ſaye,</l>
               <l>Which wedlocke do debarre,</l>
               <l>To be wicked and nought,</l>
               <l>Men in witte paſſing farre,</l>
               <l>Do iudge, and alſo ſaye,</l>
               <l>That the forefathers prudence,</l>
               <l>Weygh did not, nor perceyue,</l>
               <l>The hurtefull peſtilence</l>
               <l>That thereof did enſue,</l>
               <l>And that humayne nature</l>
               <l>Suche thinges to beare,</l>
               <l>Refuſeth, this is ſure,</l>
               <l>That Chriſt would neuer laye</l>
               <l>On vs ſo vnpleaſaunt</l>
               <l>Nor yet ſo hard a yoke,</l>
               <l>That ſtrength and might do want.</l>
               <l>Such great burden, ſay they,</l>
               <l>Whych breadeth man monſters,<note place="margin">By it he vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtandeth the ſtraunge kinde of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleneſſe that was vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Whych to many a one,</l>
               <l>Will be in ſtede of wonders,</l>
               <l>Did come and ſo procede</l>
               <l>Of bolde (what ſhould we it call?)</l>
               <l>Arrogancye? not ſo:</l>
               <l>But pitye, they do all</l>
               <l>Or godlineſſe terme it:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:7"/>
               <l>Howebeit they all affirmed</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">All maner of mens inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions cloked vnder the name and title of godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note>That ſurer it had bene,</l>
               <l>That way whych god confyrmed</l>
               <l>By his lawe to haue gone,</l>
               <l>And of the fathers auncient</l>
               <l>The trade and ſteppes eke,</l>
               <l>To haue folowed, they ment,</l>
               <l>Whoſe life, was farre better,</l>
               <l>With wife, children, and houſholde</l>
               <l>Than our life is nowe,</l>
               <l>That wifeleſſe life do hold.</l>
            </q>
            <p>¶Fyrſt and foremoſte we learne by Baptyſt Mantuan, who, as I ſayd, was a Carmelite, that Hilarius, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Poetiers was maried, &amp; that neyther his wife, nor his children, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had by her, did let him to be a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. Secondly, howe that many did complaine, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were depriued of the libertie to marye, hauing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable burdone of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie laid vpon their ſholders, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by many, not being able to beare it, were driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to commit thoſe thinges that were vnlaweful, &amp; moſt deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in goddes ſighte. And therfore he did righte well conclude, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the life of
<pb facs="tcp:6563:7"/> them in time paſt, which had wiues children, &amp; houſholdes, did farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede &amp; paſſe in godlineſſe, the life of the wiueleſſe cleargie of his time. Siluianus alſo, biſhop of Maſſilia, ſhewing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matrimony is lawful for the miniſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church,<note place="margin">Siluianus. li. v. De pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidentia dei.</note> doth ſpeak thus of the forbidding of it. <hi>Nouum pro ſus eſt conuerſionis genus, licita non faciunt, illicita committunt. Temperant a coniugio, et non tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant a rapina. Quid agis ſtulta perſuaſio? peccatae enterdizit deus, non matrimonia.</hi> That is to ſay. Truly this a newe kind of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion. They do not thoſe thinges that be laweful, &amp; commit thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, that be vnlaweful. They do ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wedlocke, but they do not abſteine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rapine. What doſt thou fooliſhe perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? God hath forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſinnes, &amp; not matrimony. Your dedes do not agre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your ſtudies. ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſay, that ye are the workers of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, ought not to be the friendes of ſinnes. This is not a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion, but an auerſion or turning away. Ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a great while a go, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> report goeth haue forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worke of honeſt ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimonye,
<pb facs="tcp:6563:8"/> ceaſſe at lenghte from wickednes.<note place="margin">Polidorus Virgilius de inuentoribus rerum. li. v. cap. iiii.</note> So farre Saluianus, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to whom Polidorus Vergilius may be ioygned, who in his bokes De in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>toribus rerum writeth on this ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner: This I am able to ſay, that it is ſo farre of, that this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtreigned cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, did paſſe the chaſtity of maryed folkes, that rather no enormytye of ſinne hathe purchaſed and broughte greater infamy &amp; ſhame to the order more hurt or harme to the religion, greater griefe to all good men,<note place="margin">Peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture may ryght wel be lefte.</note> than the blot or blemiſh of the prieſtes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continency. Therfore peraduenture it wold be bothe for the profite of the chriſtian common weale, and for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modytie of the order, that ones the right of publike mariage ſhold be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored vnto the prieſtes, whyche they mighte rather kepe godlye withoute any ſhame, than thus wyth ſuch fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy vice of nature to defile them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues moſt vncle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly.<note place="margin">Ioha. Anto. Titu. Qui clerici vel vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentes matri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monia contra here poſſunt.</note> Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes Antonius byſhop of Alexandria, doeth plainely affirme that in the primitiue church it was lawfull for Pryeſtes to haue
<pb facs="tcp:6563:8"/> wiues, yea being in the holy orders, ſo that in the time of the celebration or miniſtration of the Sacramentes they ſhuld abſteine from their wiues Afterwards a forbidding therof, dyd begin in the occidental churche, that they whych were in the holy orders, ſhould liue a continent life. Farther more this cardynall doeth ſaye, that this commaundement dyd myniſter an occaſyon to ſnare manye ſoules, and that therfore he dyd beleue, that as the Churche dyd brynge in that commaundemente of conſtreygned chaſtytye, ſo ſhe would reuoke or cal it backe agayne.<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii</note> Whyche callynge backe, ſhould be agreable with this ſayinge of Saincte Paule,<note place="margin">Panormita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> touching the Virgines, I haue no commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, but I geue conſel. The like in a manner doeth Panormitanus write, whoſe wordes for auoydynge of tediouſneſſe, and ſpecially becauſe that they do agre, wyth them that I aleaged before, I wil now omit: doth not pope Innocentius the fourth ſet forthe the ſame doctryne, ſayinge receaued
<pb facs="tcp:6563:9"/> playnely that by the law of nature, Matrimony doeth let no man to be receyued into the holy orders?<note place="margin">Innocent .4. in ſuis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentariis Titu de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. coniug. cap. placet.</note> For, by the lawe of nature, he that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued into the holy orders maye vſe matrimony ready contracted as the orientall church doth. Yea, he might alſo marrye or contract matrimony being in the holy orders, excepte the conſtitutions of the churche ſhoulde forbydde it. Wherein two thinges are playnly graunted of thys Pope. fyrſt, that they that be coupled in ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryage, maye bothe be receyued into the miniſterie, and alſo vſe (and that by the lawe of nature) in the tyme of it, theyr matrimonye. Secondlye, howe that if it were not for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions and lawes of the churche, they mighte alſo marye, after that they be called to the miniſterye.</p>
            <p>But as for the churche, this are we ſure of, that the true ſpouſe of oure ſauioure Ieſu Chryſte, wyll make no lawes and conſtytutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s contrary to the word, inſtitution &amp; ordinaunce of hyr heade and huſbande, Ieſu
<pb facs="tcp:6563:9"/> Chriſte, who in all places, bothe by him ſelfe, and by his Apoſtelles do geue vnto all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">The true church wyl make no lawes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to God his worde.</note> that haue not the gifte of continencie, free libertye to marye, and with a good conſcience, to vſe that remedy, whych god from the beginning hath appointed for al men. Therefore the conſtitutions &amp; lawes of the church,<note place="margin">Panormita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus wordes are ſo nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that I could not but bring them.</note> can not debarre from matrimonie, thoſe, that by a ſingular gift and callinge of god, be not appointed vnto a ſingle, &amp; wiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe life. Of force I am conſtrayned contrarye to that, whyche I ſayde before, to brynge in the wordes of Abbas Panormitanus,<note place="margin">Panormi. de clericis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingatis. capi. Cum olim.</note> whyche are theſe, Contine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie is not in the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, of the ſubſtance of the order, nor of the lawe of God. For, elles the Greekes ſhould ſinne: neyther ſhuld cuſtome excuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, foraſmuch as cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome ought in no wiſe to preuayle, nor to beare or haue anye place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the lawe of god. And I do not onely beleue, that the church hathe power to graunt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the cleargie may marrye, as the Greekes do, but alſo
<pb facs="tcp:6563:10"/> that this would be a wholeſome ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, for the profite &amp; healthe of the ſoules, that they, which can abſteine &amp; merite more, ſhould be left to their owne will, and that they which can not abſtayne might marry. For the experience doth teache vs, that a con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trarry effect doth enſue and folowe, of that lawe of continencie, ſith that men liue not ſpirituallye, nor be cleane, but are defyled with the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawefull vſe of women, not wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great offence agaynſt god, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as the lawefull vſe of theyr owne wyues, ſhould be chaſtitye. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the churche oughte to do, as a good phiſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which hauing learned by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that his medecine doth more hurte than good, doth remoue or take it away. Hitherto haue we taught briefely, that it is laweful by goddes worde for al them that haue not the gifte of chaſtitye, to couple them ſelues in matrimonye, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that the auncient miniſters of the prymatiue church, as Hilarius and other, had wiues, in the time of
<pb facs="tcp:6563:10"/> theyr miniſtery, whereunto I maye by the waye adde theſe wordes of Hierome: If Samuel being brought vp in the tabernacle,<note place="margin">Hieroni. lib. prun. in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinianum.</note> did marrye a wyfe, what is this preiudiciall to virginitye? Aſthough nowe in theſe dayes manye pryeſtes haue not wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues: and the Apoſtell doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe &amp; ſet forthe a byſhop to be the huſbande of one wife hauynge chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren wyth all chaſtitye? The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelle ſayeth he, was of the Iewes,<note place="margin">Idem an Oceanum.</note> and the primitiue church of Chryſte was gathered of the remnaunte of the Iewes. He knewe, that it was graunted by the lawe, and that it was by the example of the patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and of Moſes, a famyliar thing vnto the people, to get children of manye wyues. Whych priuiledge, was alſo open or free for the prye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes. He doth commaund them that the churches,<note place="margin">Math. xi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gene. ii.</note> do not chalenge or clame the like licence, and that the prieſts haue not at one time .ii. or .iii wiues, but one onely, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the firſt ordinance of god, where he ſayeth: And they ſhall be
<pb facs="tcp:6563:11"/> two in one fleſhe. We haue alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared what complaintes many god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye men haue made, that this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to marye, was by the cruell tirannye of the Roomiſhe beaſt, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from thoſe, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gift of chaſtitie was denied, &amp; howe earneſtlye they dyd deſyre, that it might be reſtored againe. Nowe, for as muche as I haue ſufficiently ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in my booke, of thoſe that by foo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhe and fond vowes not commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded of God, had raſhely and vnadui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedlye bounde them ſelues to ſingle life, or rather to vncleane chaſtitye, and vnchaſte continencie: I will ſhortly aunſwere certayne fonde ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections, that ſome worldelynges whych neuertheleſſe wil ſeeme to be earneſt fauourers of the ſcriptures &amp; of the ghoſpell of our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt, be wont to make. Although ſay they it be lawefull by gods word that miniſters ſhoulde marye, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> yet it is not expediente, that they ſhoulde haue wiues. For they that be mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed muſt care for the world, how they
<pb facs="tcp:6563:11"/> theyr wiues, and children ſhall liue, ſo that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not lightly geue theyr mindes to other thinges:<note place="margin">The fond rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons of the goſpellicke worldlinges.</note> howe can the miniſters then, beinge maryed: and hauyng houſes full of children, apply their learning, and geue them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues to heauenlye contemplation, that they may fede theyr flocke with wholeſome doctrine? The whole daye wil ſcarcelye ſerue to compaſſe and caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, howe they and theyr fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milye maye liue,<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> that we ſhoulde let paſſe this ſayenge of Paule: He that is maryed, careth for the thinges of the world, howe he maye pleaſe hys wife: whereas he that is vnmaryed, careth for the thinges of the lorde, howe he may pleaſe the lord. Again: if they be ſuffered to marye, that wil miniſter a greate occaſion to theym to be couetous, and to kepe nygarde houſes, ſo that the poore ſhall not be refreſhed by theym as they ought to be, they wyll geue theym ſelues to pourchaſe houſes and lande for theyr brottes: What hoſpitatytye then ſhall they be able to keepe? Or
<pb facs="tcp:6563:12"/> if they wil not in their life time pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for their wiues &amp; children, ſhall thei not fil the world with beggars? Theſe are the gaye paynted reaſons that our goſpellicke worldlinges be wont to aleadge,<note place="margin">Aunſwere.</note> for to put the true miniſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which is lawful by gods word,<note place="margin">Howe the text aleadged by the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaryes ought to be taken and of whom it is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded.</note> that ſo they may (whiles they maynteyne theyr expediencie, I mean that which thei call expediente) fall headlonge into that which is vnlawefull, &amp; forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of God in his holy ſcriptures. Fyrſt, as touchyng that whych they haue aleadged out of the fyrſt epiſtle to the Corinthians, it ought doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to be vnderſtanded of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that hauinge the gyfte of chaſtitye, haue no nede to marye, excepte they will, and not of them, whych for want of it are fayns to vſe the remedy which go denyeth to no man, that hathe nede of it. For, doth he not ſay a litel before: They that can not abſteyne, let them marye:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. vii.</note> It were in deede to be wiſhed, that all they that be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the miniſterye, ſhoulde be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued
<pb facs="tcp:6563:12"/> wyth that moſt excellent gyfte. But ſyth that it hath pleaſed god, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe, who diſtributeth his gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, as he knoweth to be moſte expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for his glorye: and for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte and edefy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of his churche.<note place="margin">Marke well this.</note> Who are we, that ſhuld ſtriue with god? One of theſe thre thinges muſt we nede to choſe? Eyther we muſt content our ſelues, with thoſe mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, whych ſeing, or rather feeling theym ſelues to be deſtytute of the gyfte of continencie do in the feare of god marye, that they maye kepe them ſelues vndefyled members of oure ſauioure Ieſu Chryſte: or elles we muſt call downe aungels from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to miniſter vnto vs: or if they pleaſe not, or if we can not haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as we woulde, we muſt ſuffer ſtyll thoſe fylthye whoremongers, and ſtynkynge Sodomytes, that ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med heretofore ouer all the whole worlde, to remayne ſtyll. I do not denye, but that there be ſome, vnto whom it is geuen, that they ſhoulde gelde theym ſelues, or make theym
<pb facs="tcp:6563:13"/> ſelues chaſte for the kyngedome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſake, but they are very thinne ſowen. They that be ſo, let theym with all thankefulnes employe that gift to the aduauncing and ſettinge forth of goddes glory,<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> and to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging of his kingedome, hauynge alwayes this ſayenge of Paule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes: we woulde that all our bretherne and felowe ſeruaunts were all, as we are, but euerye man hath hys proper gyfte of God, one after this maner, and an other after that. But nowe will I come to the reſt of theyr obiections. As touching the troubles &amp; cares that are commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in matrimony, we haue ſpoken of them already, ſhewinge that they do pertaine vnto the croſſe whych God wil haue to be annexed to this holye eſtate: and that for them (as I ſayde afore) no man wanting the gyfts of continencye oughte to forbeare ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony.<note place="margin">No ſtate of mans lyfe here in this world can be without trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bles &amp; cares.</note> Howebeit I woulde by the way that they ſhould ſhewe me any eſtate of mans life her vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, that can be wythoute troubles and
<pb facs="tcp:6563:13"/> cares. If any hauing the gift of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity &amp; beinge called to the miſterye, doe go aboute to kepe hoſpytalytye, how manye thinges, he ſhall daylye and hourely be troubled with al com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mune experience doeth ſufficyentlye teache vs. How many times ſhall he be faine to playe Marthas part, and by hym ſelfe to doe many thynges euery houre of the day almoſt, which yf he had a truſtye yoke felowe, he neded not to trouble hym ſelfe with all? but geue hym ſelfe quietly to his boke? Although I ſay he doth all the day long geue hym ſelfe to his owne ſtudye, beynge onelye carefull ouer the flocke of Chryſte, yet he is ſure that all thynges ſhalbe well ſeen to at home: Whereof els (ſuche is the vnfaythfulnes of ſeruauntes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out one that ſhuld alwayes ouer ſee him) he will alwayes be in doubte, and neuer be quiet in hys mynde. What ſhall we ſaye then of thoſe which beſides theſe comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> troubles and cares,<note place="margin">The intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of them that wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the gift of conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencye, and cannot be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to mary</note> do burne with the fyer of concupiſcence, and cannot be ſuffred
<pb facs="tcp:6563:14"/> to vſe the lawfull waters, that God hathe appointed, for to quenche it? Howe well (I praye you) ſhall they be able to applye theyr learnynge, and to geue them ſelues to heauenly contemplation? And as for the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of the people wyth the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye foode of Gods worde, this I am ſure, no man is able to denie, but that there haue beene more God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Sermons made in one yeare, by faythfull maryed Mynyſters, ſence oure Souerayne Lady Quene Elyzabeth dyd come in, than were made in all Queene Maryes time, by theyr wyfeleſſe and Virgyne Pryeſtes. But this is verye hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, that they doe obiecte, that ſcarcelye the whole daye wyll ſerue them, for to caſte, howe they theyr wiues, &amp; family may liue. As though whole yeares wyll ſerue theyr vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maryed Pryeſtes, that wante the gifte of contynencye, for to caſte, where they maye gette filthye har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lottes, howe they maye mayntein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them lyke gentylwomen, or rather,
<pb facs="tcp:6563:14"/> which is worſe, how they may abuſe other mens wyues, and haue theyr children to ſit by other mens fyers, were it not better, for ſuche a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſter, as hathe not the gyfte of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynencye, but yet hathe the feare of GOD before hys eyes,<note place="margin">It is not bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter in the fyghte of the worlde.</note> to care for hys owne lawfull wife, and for his children lawfullye begotten in true wedlocke, in the which he maye kepe hym ſelfe an vndefiled member of oure Sauiour Ieſu Chriſte, than to be put, for wante of hys lawfull remedye, to carke and care, and that to the vtter deſtruction of his bodye and ſoule, for a vyle ſtrumpet,<note place="margin">Sapience.</note> and hys baſtardes, whyche another daye, ſhall beare wytneſſe againſt theyr vngodlye parentes? As for the parryll of couetouſeneſſe, and the pourchaſſynge of houſe and lande for theyr brettes, wherby the maryed Mynyſters, ſhalbe faine to kepe nyggarde houſes, or to kepe leſſe hoſpytalytye, and geue leſſe relyefe to the poore, than they ought to doe. I anſwere that in this they
<pb facs="tcp:6563:15"/> may be likened vnto a certaine great vſurer,<note place="margin">This is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the wycked worldlinges.</note> who dyd hyre Preachers to Preache agaynſte vſurye, that all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beynge by the terrible threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynges of Gods worde, fraied from that abhomynable ſynne he alone myghte occupye vſurye:<note place="margin">Eſay. v,</note> In lyke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that they maye ioygne houſe to houſe,<note place="margin">A great of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, I tel you, yf the faythful my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſters ſhuld wyth theyr owne money truely gotten pourchaſſe oughte for theyr wyues and children.</note> and Lande to Lande, vntyl there bee not one plot of grounde lefte, to be gotten for mony, they wil haue none of the Cleargye to pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſſe one ſmall Cottage for theyr wyues and chyldren, to hyde theyr heades in, after theyr deceaſſe. And why, becauſe that they alone wyll reygne heare vppon the earthe, and wyll haue the whole worlde in theyr handes. But in the meane whyle, no hoſpytalytye ſhalbe kepte, and the pore ſhal want theyr due reliefe.<note place="margin">Pauperes cura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſcilicet.</note> As thoughe they care muche for the poore, whome euerye where they do moſte vngodlye oppreſſe, and wyth whoſe bloud, the morter is tempered that theyr princelyke hoſes be builded with all. Yea, are they not the
<pb facs="tcp:6563:15"/> cauſe, that the realme is ſo full of pouertye?<note place="margin">Diomedes was a cruel tyraunt whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che gaue men to hys horſes to be deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of them which thinge was ſayde of him, becauſe he cauſed the whole contry to be eaten vp with his hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſo that men coulde haue no fode.</note> Doe they not wyth theyr ſhepe (beinge in this poynte wourſe than euer Diomedes was) eate vp whole villages and townes, ſo that where ther were .xl. or .lx. plowghes going, ye ſhall now ſcarcely finde .ii. goinge? And where good fermers dwelled and kepte great hoſpitalitie reliuing the whole towneſhip, there they kepe a ſhepeheard with his boy and his dogge, ſo that a man maye aſwell breake hys necke as breake his faſte there, from whenſe afore no poore boy was ſuffered to go awaie emptie or vnrefreſhed. And yet they will ſeme to fauour hoſpytalytie, for ſothe. But it muſte be at other mens coſtes, and that they theyr ſelues maie be feaſted, &amp; haue good cheare when they come to Maſter perſons, or to maſter Vicares. For, although the faythfull Myniſter doeth to his power refreſh his pore neighbours, yet oneleſſe he doeth euerye foote feaſte theſe great cobbes, and make theim luſtye cheare, when ſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:6563:16"/> they luſte to come, he is not coump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to kepe any houſe at all. Nowe, if the paril of couetouſneſſe, whyche they wyll haue the maried miniſters to be ſo ſubiecte vnto, can debarre them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mariage, which they grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be lawfull by goddes worde, what myghte bee ſayde of thoſe that be in office vnder a prynce? myghte it not wyth a better reaſon bee ſayde, that it were moſt parillous to ſuffer them to marrye,<note place="margin">No leſſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryl of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be in office vnder a prince, than in the Miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note> lefte beynge moued wyth an inordynate deſire to leaue their wiues and children in a welthy and rich eſtate, they ſhoulde pill and pole the people, and pilfer from the prince? For, they can no more leaue theyr offices vnto their wyues and children, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the miniſters can theyr liuinges. Let any man that hath wit iudge, in whether of thoſe .ii. eſtates their is greater daunger of couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and in whether of theim coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes, can be more hurtefull to the commune weale. Howbeit, thys as the reſte is but accidentall. For althoughe ſome amonge the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
<pb facs="tcp:6563:16"/> be ſtriken wyth couetouſnes, yet manye (god be prayſed) haue the feare of God before theyr eyes, and do from the bottome of theyr hartes deteſt and abhorre couetouſeneſſe. It was not preiudicyall to the reſte of the Apoſtels, that Iudas beynge one of the .xii. was bothe couetous &amp; a thefe. Neyther ought this to moue anye man, where they ſay, that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they doe whylles they be alyue prouide for theyr wiues and children they muſt fyll the world full of beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. For they that are godlye, wyll ſee theyr Children to be broughte vp, that they ſhalbe able to make ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſhift for them ſelues,<note place="margin">Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xxxvii.</note> after theyr parents deceaſſe. Againe, is not this Dauids ſayinge: I haue ben yonge, and am olde, yet I ſawe neuer the righteous forſaken, nor his ſede beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge breade? Hereby do we learne, that althoughe the Godlye dyeth, yet his bleſſinges ſhalbe extended to his poſterytye. But in the meane ſeaſon, thys is not remembred of them, that their wifeleſſe, prieſtes do
<pb facs="tcp:6563:17"/> fille the whole worlde with whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and vnclenlines and all mens houſes with baſtardes, as muche as in them doth lie, which thinge muſt nedes kindle the wrathe of GOD a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte vs, and at lengthe to brynge the ſame vengaunce vpon the whole worlde,<note place="margin">Geneſis. xix.</note> that was by the ryghteous iudgement of God poured vpon So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Gomorre, and al the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey aboute. Sith now therfore that I haue made a ſufficient anſwere, to the foolyſhe and fonde obiections of our ghoſpellike worldlinges, I wyll make an ende, deſirynge youre good Maſterſhyppe, to take thys my rude laboure in good worthe, whyche I offer vnto you nowe at this preſent, for a ſigne of gratitude and thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, &amp; to declare that althoughe I haue not ſeen you this great while yet I am not vnmindeful of you, nor of the gentle kyndenes, that ye haue ſhewed to me warde at all tymes. Thus the lyuinge God aboue, who is the geuer of all goodnes, preſerue you and all yours and ſend you proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous
<pb facs="tcp:6563:17"/> ſucceſſe in all your godlye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres to his glorye, and youre euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting comfort.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <head>The argument of the booke.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt &amp; foremoſt, I call the enemies of the mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſters mariage, pope Euſtachians, becauſe that in this poynte, they folowe thoſe aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciente heretikes, whom they called commonly Euſtachians, whithe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yere of the lorde .324. helde opinion, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maried miniſters oughte in no wiſe to be eſtemed, yea that no man ought to receiue the holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion at the handes of theym that were coupled in matrimony, whych opinion was thoughte is ſtraunge, that then a concill was gathered &amp; aſſembled agaynſt in Gangris,<note place="margin">The canon of the concill Gangris.</note> a town of Paphlagonia, wher it was proued to be directlye agaynſt Gods worde and the truthe thereof. And therfore this canon or decree was
<pb facs="tcp:6563:18"/> made agaynſt them. <hi>Qui coniugatum preſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>biterum diſcernit, quaſi occaſione nuptiarum of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre non debeat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> et iam ab eius oblatione abſtinet, anathemaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> That is to ſaye, he that doth diſcerne or maketh a difference of a maried prieſt, although becauſe of his mariage, he can not offer, or miniſter the holy communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; doth already abſtayne from his oblation, let him be accurſed.</p>
            <p>Whereby, as I haue proued in my booke, we can iudge none other, but that the Popes catholykes, whyche do ſo abhorre maryed miniſters, makynge no conſcience at all to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the ſacramentes, at a ſorte of whoremongers handes are by their owne canons, anathema, that is to ſaye, accurſed. Agaynſt them I haue here in this ſmall treatiſe written. Fyrſte, ſhewynge that all the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that they do aleadge, both out of the olde and newe Teſtamente, for to impugne the maryage of prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, are ſhamefullye wreſted and wrethed.</p>
            <p>Secondly I haue proued, that al the
<pb facs="tcp:6563:18"/> vowes that the religious perſons, or ſecular prieſtes, dyd make, for to binde them ſelues perpetually vnto ſingle life, are directly agaynſte the holye and ſacred Scriptures, and worde of God, and that therefore they maye lawefully breake theym, and couple theym ſelues in honeſte matrimonye, that ſo liuinge in the feare of God, they maye kepe them ſelues vndefiled members of oure ſauiour Ieſus Chryſt.</p>
            <p>Thyrdelye, I haue declared moſte manifeſtlye, bothe by the examples of the Scriptures, and alſo by ſtronge argumentes taken oute of the ſame, that all religious perſons or ſeculare pryeſtes, that haue not the gyfte of chaſtitye, oughte to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye: in ſo muche that yf there be any that hauynge not the gyfte of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitye, wil not vſe the remedye, that God hathe appoynted, for all men: The Godlye Magyſtrates oughte to compelle theym, and if they be diſobedyente, to depoſe theym
<pb facs="tcp:6563:19"/> leaſt by their inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinent liuinge, thei be an offence and ſtumbling block vnto the church, and a ſlaunder vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the doctrine that thei haue taught and ſet forth. Theſe thinges haue bene done briefely and ſhortly, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge hereafter, if anye do kicke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte his doctrine, to aunſwere them fully, by the leaue &amp; aſſiſtaunce of my lord and ſauiour Ieſu Chryſt. To whom with the father, and the holy ghoſte, be all prayſe glorye, and honour, world without ende. Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>O they diſaproue the Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtelles? Peter and Philyp dyd beget children. Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p alſo did marrye his dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters to huſbandes. Neyther dothe Paule ſticke in a certayne epiſtell of his, to ſalute his wife, whych he dyd not cary about, that he might be the more readye to the miniſterye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus. Ex Euſchii hiſtoria. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Cap. <hi>30.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6563:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Do not backebite the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bleſſed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which were coupled in matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I made mention nowe. For, I wiſhe, that beyng worthy of god, I may be founde in his kingedome at theyr feete, as Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob, as Ioſeph, Eſaye, and other Prophetes, as Peter &amp; Paule, &amp; the other Apoſtels, which were coupled in matrimonie, whiche had wiues, not for to fulfil the luſts of the fleſhe, but to haue iſſue and poſteritye. <hi>Ignatius in epiſtola ad Philadelphienſes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:6563:20"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>
                  </hi> Conſcience marked wyth a hot yron what it is. 52</item>
               <item>A notable hiſtory 36</item>
               <item>A ſimilitude. 47</item>
               <item>A foolyſhe obiection. 51</item>
               <item>A compariſon betwixt the pope and Mahomet. 4</item>
               <item>A prety remedye to bryng one to the deuell. 23</item>
               <item>A canon agaynſt the makyng of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſed vowes. 33</item>
               <item>Aarons brieſthood aboliſhed. 2</item>
               <item>His prieſtes muſt haue no blemiſhe. 14</item>
               <item>Ambroſe aleadged. 24</item>
               <item>All that haue not the gifte of chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye ought to marye. 6</item>
               <item>All chriſtians are prieſtes, &amp; home. 63.</item>
               <item>Arnobius. 44</item>
               <item>Auguſtine contra Creſco. 57</item>
               <item>Vpon. 5. pſalme 44</item>
               <item>In libro heretico. 53</item>
               <item>His counſel. 34</item>
               <item>What he ſaith of them that marrye after the vowe. 35</item>
               <item>Baals prieſts and their markes. 2</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:20"/>
               <item>Baptiſme and what wee doe vowe therein. 31</item>
               <item>By it we doe become the ſeruauntes of the lorde. 32</item>
               <item>By the popes lawes Pryeſtes maye not marrye. 9</item>
               <item>Canons and rules of the apoſtels. 56</item>
               <item>Chriſte and his doctrine contrary to the pope. 56</item>
               <item>Chriſtes bodye offered once for euer. 13</item>
               <item>He hath put downe the ceremonyes of the olde lawe. 18</item>
               <item>He wyl haue vs to be free vnto him. 38</item>
               <item>He called maried men to be his apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels. 45</item>
               <item>Ciprians counſaile. 34</item>
               <item>Chriſoſtom. ad populum antioche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. 58</item>
               <item>Clemens Alexandrinus. 51</item>
               <item>Counſel of Gangris. 53</item>
               <item>And who are pronounſed accurſed by that counſell. 54</item>
               <item>Churche of Chriſte is obedyente to his wordes. 9</item>
               <item>Concluſion of vowes. 45</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:21"/>
               <item>Diſtinction. 55</item>
               <item>Doctor martine proued a lyer. 1</item>
               <item>Eufrachians. 53</item>
               <item>Euſebius eccleſiaſtical hiſtorye. 53</item>
               <item>God what he wylleth. 24.</item>
               <item>He hath appointed a remedye for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that cannot liue chaſte. 17</item>
               <item>He doeth alow the companye of man and wyfe to gether. 19</item>
               <item>Who they be that tempte hym. 16</item>
               <item>Godly Counſaile. 24</item>
               <item>Gregories repentaunce. 36.</item>
               <item>He ſaith marryage maye not be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for religions ſake. 48</item>
               <item>Huldaricus ad nicolaum papam. 36</item>
               <item>If by prieſtes we do vnderſtand my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters? all chriſtians be not prieſtes. 64</item>
               <item>Iſidorus counſaile, vpon raſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſes, 33</item>
               <item>Mahomets confeſſion. 3</item>
               <item>Matrimonye alwaies in eſtimation among the gentiles. 50</item>
               <item>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Antonius flaminius. 44</item>
               <item>Monkerye what it is amonge the Papiſt. 49</item>
               <item>Moſes example can ſerue nothinge
<pb facs="tcp:6563:21"/> for the pope. 11</item>
               <item>What he dyd commaunde the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. 10</item>
               <item>Why he did byd them refraine from theyr wyues. 10</item>
               <item>Murtherers of them ſelues. 16</item>
               <item>Papiſt firſt argument of our time. 10</item>
               <item>Theyr ſeconde argumente of oure time. 12</item>
               <item>Their third argument. 18</item>
               <item>Their forth argument. 21</item>
               <item>Their ſhameles ſhiftes. 11</item>
               <item>Their fifth argument of oure tyme. 26</item>
               <item>Their chaſtitie and to whome it is lyke. 27</item>
               <item>They haue their wife and Children ſitting by other mens fiers. 28</item>
               <item>Their ſixt argument of our time. 29</item>
               <item>Their thunder boltes. 29</item>
               <item>We muſt forſake theyr vowes. 40</item>
               <item>They are ſet forth with fayned cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie. 54</item>
               <item>Their argument beaten vpon theyr owne heades. 57</item>
               <item>They haue put on whores faces. 59</item>
               <item>They be maryed to our lady. 59</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:22"/>
               <item>Paſchal lambe. 20</item>
               <item>Paules counſayle to marryed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. 11</item>
               <item>How his wordes ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande. 26</item>
               <item>Thre thinges to be noted vpon hys wordes. 22</item>
               <item>His ſaiyng doth nothing pertaine to the papiſt. 26</item>
               <item>Prieſtes of Baal. 2</item>
               <item>Pope doth blaſpheme. 4</item>
               <item>Pope hathe all hys ſeruice in latin and why. 6</item>
               <item>He is worſe than Mahomet whyche in ſome pointe doeth geue more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour vnto chriſt then the pope. 7</item>
               <item>Prieſtes what it doth ſignifie. 8</item>
               <item>and why they be ſo called. 8</item>
               <item>Prieſtes of the old law why they dyd abſteine from their wyues. 13</item>
               <item>Prieſtes of the old law were maried 45</item>
               <item>Popiſh vowes ſeperate vs from our true ſpouſe Ieſus chriſt. 35</item>
               <item>Preachers of our time and theyr cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell tirannye. 32</item>
               <item>Spiritual whoredom. 36</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:22"/>
               <item>Single lyfe a let to thoſe that haue not the gift of chaſtitie. 22</item>
               <item>Sinedech and what it is. 48</item>
               <item>Tatius, Martion, and Manicheus, enemies of matrimony. 53</item>
               <item>The concluſion, or epilagus. 64</item>
               <item>True chaſtitie. 24</item>
               <item>The ſixte ſinode holden at Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople. 55</item>
               <item>Vowe, what it is. 29</item>
               <item>How many thinges are to be conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in making a vowe. 30</item>
               <item>We muſt make them no further the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it lieth in vs to performe them. 31</item>
               <item>What we vowe in baptiſme. 31</item>
               <item>What an vngodly vowe is. 37</item>
               <item>We muſt vow nothing that may let vs in our vocation. 38</item>
               <item>What liberty and fredom we leſe by popiſhe vowes. 39</item>
               <item>We muſt conſider the intente of our vowe. 40</item>
               <item>We may vow thoſe thinges that be indifferent and lie in our power. 41</item>
               <item>Concluſion of vowes. 43</item>
               <item>Wherein they of the olde lawe dyd confeſſe. 44</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:23"/>
               <item>What vowe god doeth require of vs 44</item>
               <item>The ende of vowes. 45</item>
               <item>What marryed men myghte haue ſaide to the Apoſtels if they hadde forſaken their wiues. 46</item>
               <item>When the Apoſtels did leaue theyr wiues, and when they did not. 47</item>
               <item>What ſacrifices the prieſtes of the new teſtament do offer. 63</item>
               <item>What ceremonies the church doeth vſe in choſinge or makynge of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. 64</item>
               <item>What god doth require of vs. 30</item>
               <item>Who they be that geld them ſelues for the kingdom of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſake. 28</item>
               <item>Why wydowes were receaued into the churche. 41.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6563:23"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:6563:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6563:24"/>
            <head>¶A ſtronge defence of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of preeſtes, made dialogue-wiſe betwixt Robin Papiſt and the true chriſtian.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>El met good neighbour and in a good tyme. I pray you, where haue ye beene theſe manye daies? Ye were not ſeen here almoſt this hole moneth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>¶Wil ye knowe wher I haue ben? I haue bene at London, I tell you: where I haue heard manye goodlye ſermons,<note place="margin">They be no lecherous prieſtes that take other mens wiues, or that haue hariottes in euery corner.</note> and ſpecially agaynſt your lecherous and carnal prieſtes, which be not aſhamed to ſaie, that they can not lyue wythoute wyues, and ſo marye, contrarye to all good order, and alſo contrarye to all godlye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, ordinaunces, and lawes, of the catholyke church.<note place="margin">A reuerend father I warrant you</note> But againſt them dyd one reuerende father Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour Martyn wryte a moſte learned and excellent worke, whyche all the heretikes in the world ſhall neuer be
<pb facs="tcp:6563:25"/> able to aunſwere or confute. I wold for your owne ſake that ye had read the hole booke through.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The true Chryſtian.</speaker>
               <p>¶I neuer reade Doctour Martyns booke: but I haue read a moſt clerke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly aunſwere, that a certayne godlye learned man, whiche nowe for the truth of gods worde,<note place="margin">Reade hys hole booke throughe and thou canſt ſay no leſſe, but that he doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in deede.</note> is fayne to flee out of his owne naturall countrey, hath made agaynſt it. Where youre Dooter Martine, is ſo handeled, that he may be aſhamed thar euer he did ſet the pen to the booke. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte in euery ſentence or lyne that he hath wrytten, he is proued to be a moſt ſhamefull lyer. But we wyll let Martines booke alone, wyth the aunſwere that hath bene made vnto it, and come to your goodly ſermons that ye haue heard. I pray you nowe what was the hole ſumme or effecte of them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">But it is law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full for them to be whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers.</note>¶The hole ſumme or effect was, that it is in no wiſe laweful for prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes to mary, and alſo, that mariage
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6563:25"/> doth let a man to be a pryeſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>¶Of what maner of pryeſtes did they ſpeake I beſeche you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>¶What Queſtion is this? Be there pryeſtes of more ſortes than of one?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chryſtian.</speaker>
               <p>¶Whye ſhould this queſtion ſeeme ſtraunge vnto you? Do ye not know that there be prieſtes of Baal,<note place="margin">2. king .xviii</note> and prieſts after the order of our ſauiour Ieſu Chryſte? For,<note place="margin">Hebru. vii.</note> of the prieſtes of Aaron, I nede not to ſpeake here, ſythe that the ſame pryeſthode, is wholy abalyſhed by our ſauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chryſte, oure ſouerayne pryeſte, whyche, (as ſaynt Paule ſayeth) ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for euer for to make interceſſion for vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>¶I knewe not ſo much. Therfore I thoughte none other, but that they ſpake of thoſe, that be pryeſtes after the order of our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>And which do ye thinke to be prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes
<pb facs="tcp:6563:26"/> after the order of our ſauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu Chryſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>☞Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe that we do commonly call: ſyr Iohn,<note place="margin">The markes of Baalles pryeſtes.</note> ſyr Thomas, ſir William &amp;c. that haue ſhauen crownes, and weare forked cappes, with long ſide gownes and tippettes: which do put on white ſurplyces on theyr garmen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, whenſoeuer they go to theyr de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruice: whyche do cenſe yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, &amp; ſay the holy and bleſſed maſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe are not prieſtes after the order of our ſauiour Ieſu Chryſt.</p>
               <p>For his prieſts do not diſguiſe them ſelues after ſuche a ſorte,<note place="margin">Read the .iii. chapter of the fyrſt Epiſtell to Timothee and the fryſte of the Epiſtel to Titus.</note> they are no ſuch marked monſters, but are kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen by other ſygnes and tokens, whych be expreſſely ſet out vnto vs in goddes booke. Therfore, thoſe are rather the pryeſtes of that ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng beaſt and Idoll Baal. Whych I do intend to proue moſt manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vnto you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>What beaſt or Idoll is it, that ye
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6563:26"/> call Baall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Wyl ye haue me to tell it you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>And I pray you ſo to do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>And wil ye not be angry wyth me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Wherfore ſhould I be angry with you: for I knowe, that for the amitie and frendſhippe, that hath bene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt you and me, euer ſins almoſte that we were but yonge babes, ye do wiſhe good vnto me, and would that I ſhoulde do no worſe then ye youre ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>¶I do vnderſtand by that beaſte or ydoll, whyche I call Baall, the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Rome: whych ye do name your holy father the Pope.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>I thought rather that by it, ye dyd vnderſtande that falſe prophete Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>I do not denye but that Mahomet
<pb facs="tcp:6563:27"/> is moſt deteſtable, and to be abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all men. But yet in compary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of your holye father the pope, in many thinges he may be accompted a ſaynct.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Howe can that be poſſible. Theſe your fayenges ſeeme vnto me very ſtraunge, yea mine eares do tinkle heare them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met touchyng our Sauyour Ieſu Chryſt.</note>Ye ſhall vnderſtande that my ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enges are moſt true. For, although Mahomet be moſte wycked and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelyſhe, yet doth he confeſſe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re ſauyour Ieſus Chryſt was conceyued and borne of a virgin, &amp; that the ſame Ieſus was in his time a gret prophete, yea that he was the wyſedome and ſoule of god. But in this he is moſt wycked, that he dothe preferre him ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chryſt, calling him ſelfe a more excellent prophete than he was, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge alſo that he is the laſt prophete of all, and that none ought to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for after hym. Agayne, he ſayeth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6563:27"/> that god hath reueled more largelye his ſecretes vnto him, than to anye other prophete that was before him. Moreouer he dothe write, that he hathe ſhewed vnto him a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte rule, than the rule of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Ieſus. This is the opinion of Mahomet. Nowe, let vs come to your holy father the pope.<note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon betwixte the Pope and Mahomet.</note> The pope doth confeſſe that Ieſus Chriſt was conceyued by the holy ghoſt, &amp; borne of a virgine, that he is the ſonne of God, and alſo that he was a greate prophete. But afterwardes, he ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as Mahomet, that is to ſaie, that he is a more excellente Prophete of God, than euer Ieſus Chryſte was. For he ſayeth,<note place="margin">The blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſaiynge of the Pope.</note> that god hath reueled vnto him, more of his ſecretes tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſaluation of men, and tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the eſtate and rule of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than vnto our ſauiour Ieſu chriſt and his apoſtles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke none other but that ye do ſlaunder him ſhamefullye.<note place="margin">He is ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red of the trueth.</note> For if he ſhould ſaye ſo, he were a verye Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:6563:28"/> and not worthy to be accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a chryſten man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ſhall be iudge your ſelfe. For I do not intende to make a lye vppon any man.<note place="margin">It is a ſhame to make a lye of the deuell.</note> Nowe marke well what I wyll ſaye, and prynte in your mynde the wordes that I ſhall ſpeake, and then I truſt that ye wil ſay as I ſay, except ye be vtterly blynded, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ouer into a reprobate ſence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>I tell you, neyghbour, as I do ſe the world to go nowe a dayes, I do not intend to ſet my ſelfe ſtyflye agaynſt the truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Ye will graunt me, that theſe are the wordes of our ſauiour Ieſu chriſt Wythout me ye can do nothyng. Meanynge thereby,<note place="margin">Iohn .xv.i.</note> that withoute his ſpeciall grace we can do nothing that is acceptable or pleaſaunt vnto god. And therfore, ſaynct Paule ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. iii.</note> that of our ſelues we be not able to thynk as much as a good thought Agayne:<note place="margin">Philippe. ii.</note> that it is god, that worketh
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6563:28"/> in vs both the will and alſo the dede But your holye father the pope ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that it lyeth in mans power, or that man hathe of his owne nature libertye to do good or euell. By the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> doctryne alſo of oure ſauioure Ieſu Chriſt, and of his apoſtelles, we do learne, that no man is able to fulfyll the lawe of god,<note place="margin">Roma. iii. Mathe. v. Gala. ii. iii.</note> wyth ſuch a perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as god doth requyre at our han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and that therfore,<note place="margin">Ephe. ii.</note> all men are of their owne nature children of wrathe, and ſubiecte to euerlaſtynge damnation. But youre holye father the pope ſayeth the contrarie, that is to ſaye, that man is able to fulfil the lawe to the vttermoſte, and to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe by his owne merites and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinges the kyngdome of heauen. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Chryſte with his apoſtles dothe ſaye,<note place="margin">Iohn. iii. v. Roma. x. Gala. iii.</note> that by the merytes onelye of his death, paſſion, and bloudſheding we are delyuered from euerlaſtynge death and damnation: but your holy father the Pope ſayeth, that the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of our owne workes, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nges may ſaue vs and that therfore
<pb facs="tcp:6563:29"/> they are neceſſary vnto ſaluation. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Ieſus Chryſt with his apoſtles doth ſaye,<note place="margin">Ioh. iii.v vi Rom. iii.iiii. Gala. ii.iii.</note> that by fayth onelye, wythout the workes of the lawe, we are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyed, and that it is the onely meane, whereby we can obtayne the free mercy of god. Naye, ſayeth your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye father the pope, we are iuſtifyed by our owne workes, &amp; by the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe and merytes of them, we do obtayne the mercye of God. Ieſus <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Chryſt doth forbyd, to ſerue or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe any other,<note place="margin">Math. iiii.v. Luke, iiii.</note> but the liuing god onely. Not ſo, doth your holye father the pope ſaye, ye ſhall beſides the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing god, worſhyppe dead creatures <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and me alſo. Ieſus Chryſt with his apoſtles doth ſaye,<note place="margin">Math. vi. Roma. x.</note> that none ought to be called vppon but God onelye, whych doctryne is confirmed by the example of all the patriarches, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, apoſtles, and martyrs of god But your holy father the pope, doth byd all men, to call vppon the deade ſaynctes, excommunicating al them <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> that will not do it.<note place="margin">Iohn. v.</note> Ieſus Chryſte with his apoſtles doth geue a ſtrayt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6563:29"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement that images ſhoulde in no wyſe be honoured or worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: But your holye father the Pope doth pronounce theym al heretykes, that will not honoure and worſhyp them. Ieſus Chryſte ſayeth, that he is the waye, the truth, and the life,<note place="margin">Iohn. xiiii.</note> and that none commeth vnto the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but by him. Agayne, the holye apoſtelles do teſtifye euerye where,<note place="margin">Roma. viii. i. Cuno. ii. i. Iohn. ii.</note> that our ſauiour Ieſus Chryſte, the onely begotten ſonne of God, is the onely interceſſour, aduocate and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour betwixt god and men: But your holy father the pope, doth bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>y affyrme, that all the bleſſed ſainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in heauen, are our interceſſours and mediators, perſecuting w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fier &amp; ſword al thoſe that wil not agree vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to his doctrine.<note place="margin">Math. xxiii.</note> Ieſus Chriſt wil not <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> haue vs to deuour widowes vnder the colour, pretence, and ſhadowe of long prayers: But your holye father the Pope wil haue al his ſhauelings to do ſo, and to deuour not onely the houſes of poore widowes, but alſo hole realmes vnder the colour &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb facs="tcp:6563:30"/> of longe prayers. Our ſauiour <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Ieſus Chryſt did geue a ſtreight com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundemente by his holye apoſtle ſaynct Paule,<note place="margin">i. Cor. xiiii.</note> that nothinge ſhoulde be done in his churche in a ſtraunge or vnknowen tounge, but that all thinges ſhould be done to the edefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge of the faythfull congregation. Naye fie, ſaieth your holy father the pope:<note place="margin">Whye Latin ſeruice is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe church.</note> that is not decente nor comely. Suche ſeruice muſte be vſed, that no man almoſt doth vnderſtand, that ſo our Catholike procedynges, beynge knowen of no man, maye the longer continew. Theſe be almoſt the chefe and principall poyntes, wherin your holy father the Pope, doth moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly preferre him ſelfe before chriſt How do ye now lyke his doynges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>¶By your ſainges, oure holy father the pope,<note place="margin">Holde thy ſelfe there Papyſt.</note> doeth compte him ſelfe wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, than our ſauyoure Ieſu Chriſte, beinge as much contrary vnto him, as Mahomet is, thoughe he wyl not be a knowen of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:6563:30"/>
               <p> ¶Naye, ye ſhall vnderſtand, that he is a greate deale worſe than Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.<note place="margin">The Pope is worſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mahomet.</note> For Mahomet is no traytoure to Chriſt, nor yet to hys churche, as your holy father the pope is, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth hym ſelfe an open enemye of his, and of all his religion. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as your holy father the Pope vnder the title and name of a true ſeruant of Chryſt, doth both betray Chryſte and his churche,<note place="margin">Math. xxvi. Mar. xiiii. Luke. xxii.</note> beyng moſt lyke vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Iudas, whych vnder the pretence and ſigne of loue, that is to ſaye, of a kyſſe, did betray his mayſter Chriſt.<note place="margin">Wherein Mahomet dyd geue more honour vnto Chriſts tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pope.</note> Moreouer, althoughe Mahomet be an enemye of Ieſu Chryſte, yet doth he geue him more honoure then the Pope doth. For, Mahomet doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and acknowledge that afore he was ſente of God, and had receyued the reuelation of his rule, who ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dyd lyue accordyng to the rule of Ieſu Chryſt, he was ſaued, and that whoſoeuer ſhall lyue accordinge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, ſhalbe ſaued. But that he ſhall not be ſo perfect, as he ſhould be, by kepynge his rule. Whereas youre
<pb facs="tcp:6563:31"/> holy faher the pope dothe playnelye affyrme, that no man can be ſaued by keping of Chriſtes rule onely, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte he doth alſo kepe his conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, lawes and ordinaunces, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge that we muſt obſerue and kepe them, if we wyll be perfect Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Is not this to ſay, that he kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth more of the ſecreetes of God, than our ſauiour Ieſus Chryſte, or his apoſtles dyd?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>Let vs leaue the pope to his great iudge our ſauiour Ieſu Chryſte, and come to the matter that we began wythall. Dyd Chryſte no where in all his goſpell forbyd, that pryeſtes ſhould marye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Afore we do beginne, or go any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">What is ment by thys worde prieſt.</note> wyth the matter, ye muſte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what we do meane by this word, pryeſt: for many are deceyued in it. For they thinke that it dothe onelye ſignify them, that weare ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen crownes, and whyte ſurplyces vpon theyr long ſide gownes, and ſuche
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6563:31"/> other gugawes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>What doth it ſignifye I praye you? hath it any other ſignification than we do geue it commonly?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>This name prieſte cometh of this greke word, preſbiter,<note place="margin">What thys word, prieſt, doth ſignifye</note> which in our Englyſhe doth betoken an elder.</p>
               <p>Nowe if ye aſke me whether Chriſt hath forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elders of his church to mary, I aunſwere vnto you, that ye ſhall finde no where in all the whole bodye of the ſcriptures, that they are more forbydden to marye, then the other chriſtians are, which of the holy apoſtel ſaynct Peter, are al called a ſpiritual prieſtehoode, for to offer ſpirituall oblations and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafices vnto almighty god.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Yf this word prieſt doth ſignify an elder, why do we call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſerue in oure churches prieſtes, ſithe that
<pb facs="tcp:6563:32"/> they be for the moſt part,<note place="margin">If he can ſay a maſſe, he is fit ynough to be ſir Iodn.</note> yong boies and laddes? For in theſe oure dayes they do preeſte ſome, that be ſcarcely xviii. yeres olde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>¶They be ſo called, becauſe of the auncientnes,<note place="margin">Why the miniſters of the church be called prieſts or elders.</note> wyſedome, and ſobre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and alſo for the great learning and diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhould be in them. For, this word elderſhippe, doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and ſignifye al theſe thinges. Yf they be not then auncient in age they ought to be auncient in wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knoweledge, and alſo in example of godly conuerſation, and liuing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe therfore I do aſke you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt hath not forbydden ſuch prieſtes or miniſters of his church to marye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>No verelye, as ye your ſelfe ſhall eaſely perceyue, if ye will reade di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentlie the ſcriptures, both of the old and newe Teſtament.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:6563:32"/>
               <p>As I haue ſayd vnto you already, our preachers of London do ſtoutely affyrme, that it is in no wiſe lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for a pryeſte to marye, nor for a man that is maryed, to be a pryeſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>In deede it is not lawefmll for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe prieſtes to marye,<note place="margin">what pryeſts they be that may not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye.</note> if they wyll folowe the ordinaunces, conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and lawes of your holye father the pope. For according to his rule, he hathe rather that his pryeſtes be whoremongers. Sodomites, and fil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thye adulterers, as he is him ſelfe, than that they ſhould be honeſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried men, according to the inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſauiour Ieſu Chryſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>Howe knowe ye that to be true?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>God wot, it is very eaſy to be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen. For if one of his pryeſtes be found or taken in aduoutrye,<note place="margin">Good iuſtice I warrant you.</note> or in whoredome, by geuyng the byſhop a noble or two, or by bryngyng a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or two of fatte capons vnto the commiſſarie, he ſhalbe quittted, and
<pb facs="tcp:6563:33"/> let go:<note place="margin">But vppon a condition, that he doe it warely after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes.</note> but if anye of them ſhould go about to take a wife, and ſo marye according to the inſtitution and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of god, for to kepe him ſelf an vndefiled membre of our ſauiour Ieſu chryſt, he ſhall be brent vp lyke an heretike, whereby ye may knowe that he hath rather that his pryeſtes ſhould walowe in fylthye and ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge whoredome,<note place="margin">It is a plaine blaſphemye agaynſte the god in earthe ſo to doe.</note> than that they ſhould ones marye, and that he doth eſteme it to be a greater ſinne to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, than to be a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon whorehunter</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>But they ſaye, that the church hath ſo ordeyned long a go.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>The tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chryſtian.</speaker>
               <p>I graunt that the popiſhe church hathe ſo ordeyned, but not the true church of Chriſte.<note place="margin">i. Timo. iii. The true Churche of Chryſte doth ſet forthe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the lawes and worde of God.</note> For the true and faythfull churche of our ſauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chriſt, which is the houſe of god, the piller and ſtaye of the truth, will neuer take vpon her to ſet forth any thing contrarye to the minde of her true huſband and head, our ſauiour Ieſu Chryſte, nor yet to teache anye
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6563:33"/> thing, that might hinder the liberty and fredome, that he hath both pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed and geuen vnto his faythfull ſeruaunts and miniſters. This true and faythfull churche, I ſaye, ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her ſelfe to be ruled, guyded, and gouerned by the onelye worde and ſpiryte of her head and mayſter our ſauiour Ieſu Chryſte, will in no wiſe preſume to forbidde any thinge that our ſauiour Ieſus Chryſte hath commaunded, nor to commaunde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that he hath prohibited and forbydden.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>But they do ſtoutelie maynteyne that this is done accordinge to the ſcriptures and worde of god.<note place="margin">Exod. xix. The fyrſte argument that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes of oure time do bring againſte the maryage of pryeſtes.</note> For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the euerliuing and eternal god, did go about to deliuer his lawe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Moſes, the ſame Moſes being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpyred of the holye ghoſte, did geue a commaundement vnto the people that they ſhould abſtayne from theyr owne wiues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:34"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aunſwere to it.</note>That example ſerueth nothynge for the popyſhe church, if ye do well conſider the wordes of Moyſes. For he did generally forbydde al the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to come to theyr wiues: but your holy father the pope doth onelye for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bydde his prieſtes. Agayne, Moſes ſaith not: I commaund &amp; charge you that ye neuer come to your wiues,<note place="margin">Exo. xix.</note> or that ye neuer mary: but ſaith only be ready agaynſt the third day, &amp; come not at your wiues. As if Moſes wold haue ſayde: Ye muſt ſanctifye your ſelues theſe three dayes: therfore ye ſhall ceaſſe from all your bodelye la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures, and workes, and alſo from the vſe of your owne wiues, that ye may the better praye vnto God, and thinke on thoſe thinges, that God hathe appoynted to do on the thyrde daye. Ye ſee that Moſes doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the people to abſtayne from theyr bodelye laboures,<note place="margin">why the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was byd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frame from their wyues.</note> and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng wyth theyr wyues, onelye for three dayes, that they myghte be the more readye both to praye, and alſo to receyue the highe miſteryes, that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6563:34"/> God has appoynted to ſhewe vnto them the thyrd daye.</p>
               <p>The lyke dothe the bleſſed Apoſtell ſaynct Paule ſay vnto all chriſtians that be maryed, ſpeakyng after this maner:<note place="margin">i. Corin. vii. This place ſhalbe more largelye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teewardes, aboute the middes of the booke.</note> wythdrawe not your ſelues one from an other, except it be with conſente for a time, for to geue your ſelues to faſtynge and prayer. And afterwardes come together againe, leaſt Sathan tempt you for your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continenci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ye ſee that Sayncte Paule will not haue a man to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe him ſelfe from his wyfe, nor the wyfe from her huſbande, but as farre forthe as the one can forbeare the other. And if ye conſider wel the wordes of Sayncte Paule, ye ſhall ſoone perceyue, that he wil not haue the man and the wyfe to be longe a ſunder, leaſte Sathan the Deuell do tempt them, and make theym to fall into ſome abhominable ſin, through theyr incontinencye. For as a man can not alwayes praye and falſe, ſo can not he be alwayes wythout his o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne wyfe. For, to praye, to faſte,
<pb facs="tcp:6563:35"/> and to liue chaſtely without the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany of a woman, are ſpecial giftes of almighty God, whyche he geueth to whom it pleaſeth him, and for as long as he thinketh it expedient.</p>
               <p>Marke then that Moſes did not giue a commaundemente to the pryeſtes onelye, that they ſhoulde abſtayne from they wiues,<note place="margin">The example of Moyſes can ſerue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng for the Pope.</note> but alſo to the hole people. Therfore, if your holye father the pope, wyll haue this place to ſerue for his purpoſe, he muſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well forbydde all the chryſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to marye, as his pryeſtes. For whye? The one doth ſtande wyth no more reaſon than the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Our holye father the pope, doth forbydde pryeſtes to marye, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> becauſe that they are appoynted in the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, to miniſter the holye miſteryes vnto the people, and alſo, becauſe that they are mediatoures betwixt god and vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> I aunſwere, that Moſes was then the onelye miniſter of the churche;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6563:35"/> and as a mediatour betwyxte God and the people. And yet he doth not ſeparate him ſelfe alone from hys wyfe, for thoſe three dayes, but alſo commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth al the people to do the ſame.<note place="margin">This the papyſtes wyl neuer graunt</note> Do not the holye ſacramentes and miſteryes pertayne to the hole churche, I meane, to all theym that be Chriſtians as well, as vnto the prieſts and miniſters of the church? I ſaye, that they can no more cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge vnto them ſelues of thoſe holy miſteries and ſacramentes by any ryghte or priuiledge, that they haue geuen them of God, than the leaſte chriſtian in the world, ſauing onelye that they are miniſters of them, for to diſtribute and geue them vnto the people, thereunto prepared and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned. Nowe if the dignitie &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of the thinges that be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, doeth require that the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters be vnmaried, howe much more doth it require, that they whyche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue ſuch holye miſteries ſhould be vnmaryed? For if the maryage doth defile the miniſter, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth miniſter holi thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs, how much more
<pb facs="tcp:6563:36"/> doth it defyle thoſe that receyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? If the miniſter ought to be holye in the miniſtration of the holy and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred miſteries, muche more oughte they, to whom they be miniſtred to be holy It is plaine &amp; manifeſt then, that the pope hath no more cauſe to forbidde prieſtes to marye, than all the reſt of the people. For, whether is the miniſtration of the ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, more precious and excellente, then the receyuing of them is?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond argumente of the papiſt of oure tyme.</note>I can ſaye nothing agaynſte your argumentes, but yet our preachers do ſaye, that the prieſtes of the olde lawe, dyd abſteyne from their owne wiues duringe the time of theyr of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and miniſtration in the temple. As it appeareth by Zacharie the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Iohn Baptiſt.<note place="margin">Luke .i.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>This example doth ſerue for me, and not for them. For by it, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſtly proued, that the pryeſtes of the olde lawe had wiues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:6563:36"/>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>It is true. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> But if the Pryeſtes of the olde lawe, dyd abſteine from theyr wifes, when they came to the alter, for to offer ſacrifyces in the temple, how muche more ought the pryeſtes of the new Teſtament,<note place="margin">Where there is forgeuenes of thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, there is no more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for ſynne. Hebre. x.</note> to liue chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, all the dayes of theyr lyfe, ſythe that they haue ſuche an hyghe ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to offer vnto God daylye for the ſynnes of the people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>I wold faine know, what ſacrifice the pryeſtes of the newe Teſtament haue to offer vnto God dayly for the ſinnes of the people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Doe they not offer our Sauyoure Ieſu Chriſte, I praye you, bothe god and man, vnto his heauenly father, for the ſinnes both of the quicke and of the deade.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>It hath bene alredy ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, in the firſt talke,<note place="margin">In the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe of the Maſſe.</note> that we had together a prety while a goe, what a blaſphemie it is to ſaye, that Chriſte
<pb facs="tcp:6563:37"/> can be offered any more.<note place="margin">Reade alſo of this in the vi. Dialogue of my true buckeler and ſhylde of the Chriſtian faythe and in my confeſſion vpon the Crede. Hebre, x.</note> For, it is to aboliſhe and put downe that omny-ſufficyent ſacrifice whiche oure Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour Ieſus Chryſt the highe prieſt dyd offer once for euer vppon the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the croſſe, and to make it of no more efficacie, ſtrength and valew, than the ſacrifyces of the olde lawe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>I haue not yet forgotten, what was ſayde then. Therfore, ſhew me nowe, why the pryeſtes of the olde lawe dyd abſteine from theyr wiues in the tyme of theyr Mynyſtration and office.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Your holye father the Pope, wold gladlye ſet vp agayne, all the ſhado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes and figures of the olde lawe, whyche oure Sauyour Ieſus Chriſt hathe abollyſhed.<note place="margin">Why the pryeſtes of the olde lawe dyd abſteyne from theyr wyues.</note> Ye ſhall therefore vnderſtande, that the pryeſtes of the olde Teſtamente, dyd abſteyne from theyr wyues, durynge the tyme of theyr office, for to repreſente, and ſygnyfye, the integrytye and pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that ſhoulde be in oure Sauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6563:37"/> Ieſu Chryſte the eternall and euerlaſtynge pryeſte, whoſe fygure they were onelye. But it alſo they did ſignifie and repreſent that he ſhould be conceaued by the holy ghoſt, with oute the ſeede or operation of man.</p>
               <p>Nowe theſe ceremonyes are ceaſſed and fully ended, after that oure Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſte the eternal and euerlaſtynge pryeſt after the order of Melchiſedech, hathe offered hym ſelfe a ſacrifice vnto God his father, for the redemption of all mankynde, as he hym ſelfe dyd teſtifye vpon the croſſe, ſayinge: It is finiſhed. Elles,<note place="margin">Iohn .xix.</note> yf Chriſtians were compelled to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the ceremonies of the old law, they might haue no prieſtes but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynred and Trybe of Leuye.<note place="margin">But thoſe are moſt mete for to be prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes nowe a dayes.</note> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, they myghte haue no prieſtes, that were myſſhapen, and that had anye blemyſhe or fawte in theyr bodies. For, theſe be the words, that Moyſes is commaunded to ſpeake vnto Aaron: Whoſoeuer of thy ſede in theyr generations,<note place="margin">Leuit. xxi.</note> hathe anye deformitye let hym not preaſe for to
<pb facs="tcp:6563:38"/> offer breade vnto his god. For, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hath any blemyſhe, ſhall not come nere, as yf he be blind or lame, or that hathe a bruiſed noſe, or that hathe anye myſhapen member or is broken, footed, or broken handed, or hathe no heares on his eye browes, or be maunge, or ſkaulde, or hathe hys ſtones broken.<note place="margin">So long doth the pope fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the olde lawe, as he doeth thinke it to be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for hym and his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</note> No man that hathe a blemyſhe, and is of the ſeede of Aaron the prieſte, ſhall come nigh to offer the ſacrifices of the Lorde.</p>
               <p>But now, your holy father the pope doeth cleane contrary. For, he doeth alowe them for prieſtes, whyche are miſſhapen, and whiche haue defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myttes and blemyſhes in theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, wherin he doeth well declare, that the Chriſtians are not ſubiecte vnto the ceremonyes of the old law.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">There is a good cauſe whye.</note>Yet he wyll alowe none that haue broken ſtones, or that lacke them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">If the prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes had no ſtones, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture there myghte be leſſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes in the paryſhes where they doe ſerue.</note>Wyl ye knowe the cauſe why he doeth it? harken in your eare, and I wyl tel it you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:6563:38"/>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Go to, goe to: ye wyl be olde Iohn ſtil. But now without all geſtynge, tel me why god wolde haue none to be made pryeſtes, that had anye fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in theyr bodyes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>For to ſignifie thereby the greate integritye and perfection, whyche ſhoulde be in the hygheſt prieſte of all, which is our ſauiour Ieſu chriſt. But marke ye this beſides: yf youre hole father the pope, wyl folowe the law of Moiſes, he muſt nedes forbyd the prieſtes, that duringe the time of theyr office, which, as ye ſaye, doeth continew all the dayes of theyr lyfe, they ſhoulde drinke no wine,<note place="margin">Thys law wold in no wyſe pleaſe the pryeſtes of our tyme. For they loue good drinke to well.</note> nor no kinde of ſtronge beere or ale. For thus ſayth the lord vnto Aeron: rhou and thy ſonnes, ſhal drinke no wine nor any kind of ſtrong drinke, when ye ſhall come into the tabernakle of witneſſe. He muſt alſo forbyd them to ſhaue theyr heades,<note place="margin">Leui. xxi</note> and the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of theyr beardes. For, God dyd forbyd the pryeſtes of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:6563:39"/> the ſame. Anye man maye ſee that the Pope hathe no more iuſte cauſe to forbyd hys prieſtes to mary, than to forbyd them the other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges heretofore reherced and named. Wherefore,<note place="margin">The ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of the pope is a ioly bayte for the deuel, for to ketche the ſoules of men and women with all.</note> all that he doeth, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge elles but a playne tyrannye, whereby he doeth caſte awaye the ſoules not onely of hys pryeſtes, but alſo of manye pore women and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and alſo whereby he doeth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender in the worlde a moſt deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble whoredom, and filthy Sodomy. Whe doeth he preſume, I beſeche you, to commaunde anye man, that hathe not the gyfte of chaſtytye, to liue withoute the remedie that God hathe appoynted for euerye man? If a Prieſte hathe the gifte of chaſtetie, he nedeth not to commaunde him to liue chaſtelie, yf he hathe it not, why doeth he laye ſuche an heauye yocke vpon his necke? Doth the Pope and his prieſts thinke to rule god as they liſt?<note place="margin">He may if he lyſt, for he is god in earthe.</note> if your holy father the pope hath ſuch a delight to haue his prieſtes to be wiueleſſe: why doeth not he hym
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6563:39"/> ſelfe geue them the gift of chaſtitye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>God onely geueth the gifte of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie, as he doeth all other giftes: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> therefore, they muſte aſke it of him, with faithfull and earneſt prayers, and withoute doubte they ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine it. For, oure Sauioure Ieſus Chriſte ſaieth:<note place="margin">Math. vii. Mar. xi. Luke. xi.</note> Aſke, and it ſhall be geuen vnto you: Seke and ye ſhall finde, Knocke, and it ſhall be open vnto you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>What ſoeuer is neceſſarye vnto ſaluation we haue a promiſe in the ſcriptures that we ſhall obteine it of God, if we doe aſke it in faithe.<note place="margin">Aunſwere.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Agayne, where haue they a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe that god wyll geue the gyft of chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye vnto all thoſe, that the pope doth forbyd to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye.</note> But howe ſhall ye be able to proue, that to lyue withoute a wife, is a thinge neceſſarye vnto ſaluacion? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if a man, not hauinge the gifte of chaſtitie, or not being called there to of the Lorde, doeth wilfullye and for hys owne pleaſure ſeperate or bannyſhe hym ſelfe for euer frome the holye eſtate of Matrymonye, he doeth moſte paryllouſlye tempte
<pb facs="tcp:6563:40"/> god. For whoſoeuer he be that wyll not vſe in his neceſſity,<note place="margin">What it is to tempt god</note> the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural remedy that god hath ordeined and appoynted, withoute all doubte he doeth tempte God. Euen as yf a man wolde neither eate nor drinke, though hunger dyd come vpon hym neuer ſo muche, but forſak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nge all kinde of meates and drynkes, that god hath ordeined for the vſe of man he ſhould deſire of God that he wold take awaye hys hunger by his abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute power. Should not ſuche a man tempte God? wold ye not iudge ſuch a man to be a deſpyſer of the ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces of the Lord. And if he ſhold dye,<note place="margin">Murtherers of them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues</note> wolde ye not iudge hym to be a murtherer of him ſelfe? I ſay, that it is as harde for a man, whiche hathe not the gifte of chaſtitie, to kepe him ſelfe from falling into ſinne, as it is for him to lyue withoute meate and drinke,<note place="margin">Math. iiii.</note> without the ſpeciall gyfte of the Lorde. We doe reade that oure ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt dyd faſt fortye dayes &amp; .xl. nyg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts, and that al that ſpace he did neither eate nor drynke,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6563:40"/> but that he dyd hunger at lengthe, and that the Aungels minyſtred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. Whereby it doeth appeare, that when he was a hungerd, he did both eate and drinke, vſing the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full remedies and meanes, that hys heauenly father hath appointed.<note place="margin">When the gift of chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is taken away from a man, he muſt vſe the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye that God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> So it hapneth many tymes, that a man hath the gifte of chaſtitye for a time, but that afterwardes it is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye from hym. Then muſte he vſe the remedye, that god hath appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ordeyned, is it not to tempe God, whan a man feelinge the fyer of concupyſcence, that burneth and tormenteth hym, if he wyll not vſe the water, that GOD offreth vnto him, whiche is maryage?<note place="margin">Mariage is the lawefull water for to quenche the fyer of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence.</note> It is euen as if a man ſeinge hys houſe on fier, wolde not vſe the waters that be rounde aboute it, for to quenche the burnynge, but wold ſay, let it alone, God will quenche it. Verelye, I ſay vnto you, that whoſoeuer doeth in his neceſſitie deſpiſe the ordynaunce of god, and hathe lieffer burne than to mary, he ſhal neuer be chaſte, but
<pb facs="tcp:6563:41"/> his bed ſhal alwaies be polluted and defiled:<note place="margin">The puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of thoſe that deſpiſe matrimonye.</note> and as long, as he ſhall deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe the holye eſtate of matrimonye or refuſe to vſe it, god will neuer geue him the gift of chaſtety, but ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer him to burne, and to be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his fleſhe, and to fall from one ſinne into another. For do ye thinke that god doth loue them, that do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpyſe his ordeynaunces in theyr ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie? Do not ſuch perſons declare them ſelues to be moſt vnthankeful vnto him? In dede if a man be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to be awaye from his wife for a time,<note place="margin">When we oughte to praye moſt earneſtlye for the gifte of chaſtitye.</note> for to folowe his vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that god hathe called him to: it is his duetye to pray vnto god, that he voucheſafe to mortifye and quenche ſuche fyer of concupiſcence in him, duringe the time, that he is awaye from his wife, and truly ſuch a man oughte to beleue that god wil heare him, if he doth praye wyth a fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart, hauinge the feare of God before his eyes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>This beſydes, they ſayde, in theyr
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6563:41"/> ſermons, that when Dauid came to Abimelech, and required him that he would geue him of the holy loues whych they call the ſhewe breade:<note place="margin">i. Samu. xxi. The thyrd ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gument of the papiſtes of our time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> or euer Abimelech the highe prieſte woulde geue him anye, he dyd aſke him, whether both he and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions has kept them ſelues clene from theyr wiues. And hereupo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did they aledge ſayncte Hierome, who writinge vppon the epiſtell to Titus, doth ſaye theſe wordes: The ſhewe breade did ſignify and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the bodye of oure ſauioure Ieſu Chriſte. Therfore, let theym,<note place="margin">Hierome vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell to Titus</note> that will eate the bodye of our ſauioure Ieſu Chriſte, abſtayne from theyr wiues. For if ſuche a cleanelineſſe was required, for to eat of the ſhewe breed, howe much more is it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,<note place="margin">A goodly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, I aſſure you.</note> when we go to feede vppon the precious body and bloude of oure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſu Chriſt? Therfore, ſaye they, ſith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſts do dayly make the precious bodye of Chriſt, &amp; alſo eate it, in theyr holy &amp; bleſſed maſſe, it is in no wiſe lawful for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mary.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:42"/>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aunſwere.</note>All this maketh nothing agaynſt me. For, Abimelech him ſelfe the hygh prieſte was maryed. Therfore they can not proue by this, that the pryeſtes oughte alwayes to be put frome the benefyte of holy wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> But why did Abimelech aſke, whether Dauid and his company<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, were clene, and ſpecially from women?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chryſtian.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aunſwere.</note>Becauſe that the lawe did then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre ſuche an outwarde holyneſſe, and bodily purifienge. If anye had touched but a dead corps,<note place="margin">Leui. xi.xv.</note> or had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered anye pollution in the night, it had not bene lawefull for theym to touche holy thinges, nor yet to come nere the people or the tabernacle, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they had bene purified before.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſt hath put downe al the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes of the olde lawe.</note>But all ſuche ceremonies, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or bodilye purifienges, are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by our ſauiour Ieſu chriſt who dothe onelye require nowe the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6563:42"/> pureneſſe of the hearte, as he him ſelfe doth teſtifye, ſayeng:<note place="margin">Math. v.</note> bleſſed are they that are cleane of heart, for thei ſhall ſee god. Nowe, this clenelines is obtayned by faythe, wythoute the ceremonies of the lawe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>But what ſaye ye to ſayncte Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roms wordes? Me thinke that they do make directly agaynſt you.</p>
               <p>I would fayne heare what aunſwer ye can make to them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>This aunſwere do I make: both ſayncte Hieromes wordes, and alſo your ſayenges were moſte true, if Chryſte and commaunded any ſuch thyng. But as I haue ſayd alreadye before, he hathe vtterlye abolyſhed and put downe,<note place="margin">The honeſte companynge of a man and a woman to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in wedlocke is pure and holy before God.</note> all ſuch ceremonies and bodilye purifyenges. And nowe the honeſte cohabitation or compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeng of man and woman together in the holye eſtate of matrimonye, doth in no wiſe pollute or defile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but that they maye at all times vſe
<pb facs="tcp:6563:43"/> and receiue the holy ſacramentes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. xiii.</note>Doth not ſ. Paule ſay that wedlocke is honourable amonge all men, and that the bed of them, that be maried in the lord, is vndefyled.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robin Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> Yet the ſayeng of ſaynct Hierome doth ſtyll ſtycke in my minde. And verely me thinke that it agreeth beſt with the truth. For, if it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, taht they which would eate of the ſhewe breade, ſhoulde abſtayne from their wiues: howe much more is it neceſſarye, that they that eate the bodye of Chriſte daylye, as the prieſtes do, ſhould kepe them ſelues chaſte, and be altogither withoute wiues? If the eating of the figure doth require ſuch a clenelineſſe from women, what ſhall the veritie of the thing it ſelfe do?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>What we oghte to iudge of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente of the bodye and bloude of Chriſt,<note place="margin">In my lyghte ſkirmiſhinge againſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cus antonius</note> it hath bene metely well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in our ſecond talke and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitation, that we had laſte toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6563:43"/> ſaue this. Therfore wil I leaue the ſawe, and come to your ſayeng, whiche is this: If it was neceſſarye ſaye ye, that they, whych would eate of the ſhewe breade, being but a bare figure, ſhoulde abſteyne from theyr wiues: Howe much more is it neceſſary, that they, whych eate the bodye of Chriſte daylye, as the prye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes do, ſhoulde kepe theym ſelues chaſte and be altogither withoute wiues?<note place="margin">Aunſwere.</note> Ye ſhall ſoone perceyue how weake your argument is.<note place="margin">Exod. xii.</note> God gaue a commaundemente, that when the paſchall lambe ſhould be eaten, the Iſraelites ſhoulde vſe no leuened bread by the ſpace of ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> daies, and that whoſoeuer did eate or kepe any in his houſe, al that while, his ſoule ſhould periſhe from among his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Nowe may I make mine argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after this maner:<note place="margin">The one ſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth with as good reaſon as the other.</note> If it was ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſarie, that they which did eate the paſchal la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be ſhould abſteine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned bread, not only whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they did eat the Eaſter, but alſo, hole ſire dayes after: how much more is it requiſite
<pb facs="tcp:6563:44"/> and neceſſarye, that they whyche do eate the ſacrament of the bodye and bloud of Chryſt, which as ye ſay all, was figurate, ſignified, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the paſchall lambe, ſhould abſtaine from leuened bread? Yea, how dare your pryeſtes eate any le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uened breade at anye time, ſith that they do eate and drinke the bydy and bloud of Chriſt almoſt euery day?<note place="margin">He will do it for al that, and who ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doth ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary ſhal frie a faggot. Epheſi.</note> It is eaſye nowe to perceyue, that your holy father the pope hath no cauſe at all to bring it to be church of chriſt, whether it be in generall or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, ſuch outward and bodely ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fienges or purifienges, excepte he will tourne all the hole chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion into a Iuiſhe ſuperſition, and make the comming of our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſu chryſt vnprofitable, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the alliaunce, agrement, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction that Ieſus Chryſte hath made of the two peoples, I meane, the Iewes and the Gentiles by abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing and putting downe the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, to be of no effect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:6563:44"/>
               <p>Ye ſhall not ſo eſcape. For they did bring an other ſtronge argumente,<note place="margin">The forthe argumente of the Papiſtes of oure tyme. i. Corin. vii.</note> whyche they grounde vpon Paule, where he exhorteth them that be ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryed, to forbeare the libertye of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, for a time, that they maye the better geue them ſelues to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Syth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that prieſtes are bound to miniſter continualli in the church and alſo to praye dayly for them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and for the people, the churche had a iuſt cauſe to forbydde them to marye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Did they alleadge the hole ſentence as it lyeth in the text?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>They did alleadge it none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then I haue rehearced it vnto you already.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Ye may ſee what theues they are,<note place="margin">The foule ſhyfte of the Papiſtes.</note> they ſteale in a maner the hole ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence form the people, leaſt the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ignoraunt ſhould eſpye oute theyr iuggelyng. The wordes are theſe: Withdrawe not youre ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:6563:45"/> one from another, except it be wyth conſente for a time, for to geue youre ſelues to faſtinge and prayer. And afterwardes come together againe, leſt Sathan doe tempte you for your incontinencie. I haue now reherced the hole ſentence vnto you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>As farre as I doe remember, we haue had the ſame ſentence alredye before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>It is moſte true. Nowe, by theſe wordes,<note place="margin">In the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of the fyrſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente. Aunſwere.</note> Saint Paule doth not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde but exhorte them, that be maryed, if theyr mutuall dwellynge or companieng together, be a let vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, that they cannot geue them ſelues to prayers and faſtynge, to withdrawe them ſelues one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, but yet wyth conſente, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge if they haue bothe the gyfte of continencye, duryng the tyme of the faſtinge and prayer, and be able to forbeare one another. But what doeth it folowe? Afterwardes come
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6563:45"/> together agayne, leſte Sathan doe tempte you, for your incontinencye, ſayeth he. As if he ſhould ſaye: if du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ynge the tyme of youre faſtyng and prayer, ye do feele that ye cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raine or lyue chaſtelye, come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her agayne, leſt Sathan vnder the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hadowe and coloure of your faſting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd prayer doe tempte you. Beware <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n any wiſe that ye geue no occaſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto Sathan to tempt you,<note place="margin">Thee thyngs to be noted vpon Paules wordes.</note> for your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncontinencie. Vppon whyche wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es thre thinges are to be notes.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, that the bleſſed Apoſtel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oeth onely ſpeake vnto thoſe, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y mutuall companyeng together, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re letted to faſt and to pray. where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon I may make an argument af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er this ſorte. Yf we muſt leaue of, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he mutuall companyeng together <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Matrimony, durynge the tyme, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat it doeth let vs to faſte and pray, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y muche more ſtrong reaſon, ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to forſake &amp; leaue all other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es that doe let vs to praye or to doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe thinges, that perteyne to oure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccacion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:46"/>
               <speaker>Robyn Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>I doe confeſſe that to be true. But what wyll ye make of it? I woulde fayne heare what ye wyll ſaye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>For to helpe the weake memory of the ſimple and vnlearned, I wyl be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne againe mine argumente. If, as I ſayed before, the mutuall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paniyng together in holy matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye and wedlocke, muſt be forborne for a whyle, I meane durynge the time, that it doeth let vs to faſte and praye, how much more ought we to forbeare, yea and to forſake all other thinges, that doe hynder and let our praiers.<note place="margin">The ſyngle lyfe is a let vnto thoſe pryeſtes that haue not the gifte of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtytye.</note> But to liue a wiueleſſe life, doeth let the pryeſtes, whyche haue not the gifte of chaſtitye, to praye, and to do other thyngs that perteine to theyr office and vocation: Ergoe they ought to forſake that kynde of lyfe, and to be at defiaunce wyth it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>I denye the minour or ſecond part of your argument.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:6563:46"/>
               <p>I deſire no better than the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men experience, whych we ſee dayly before oure eyes, for to proue it.<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men expery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence proueth all.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Whervnto might be added the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of Sainct Paule whiche we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed euen now. Do we not ſee dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, I praye you, yf a pryeſt hath not the gyfte of chaſtitye, that where as he ſhould ſtudye and praye,<note place="margin">This is to true.</note> he doeth occupye hym ſelfe all the daye long, in ſeekynge of hys harlottes and whores, and yf the finde none at the firſte, he doeth vexe hym ſelfe, nyght and daye, ſtudying, howe he maye, by one meane or other, brynge ſome honeſt poore woman or mayde to naught? And verelye, yf this fyer of incontinencye, whyche he burneth wyth all, bee not quenched by one naughtie meane or other, he ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be able, to praye, to reade, or ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, he ſhal neuer thinke of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye thinges, not yet on anye thinge, that is good. Theſe thinges beynge conſydered a ryghte,<note place="margin">i. Timo. iiii.</note> it is an eaſye thinge to perceyue, that thys wyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe lyfe, whych truelye is a plaine
<pb facs="tcp:6563:47"/> inuention of the deuell, doeth alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether let theym, that haue not the gyfte of continencye and chaſtytye, to doe the thynges that pertayne to theyr vocation and callynge. Let theſe wyueleſſe preeſtes, what fayre face ſoeuer they beare before men, and how ſoeuer they doe diſſemble, and cloke the fier of incontinencye, that they burne wythall, be iudge theyr ſelues. I doe onelye appeale to theyr owne conſcience, whych nowe is, and ſhalbe hereafter a ſufficiente withneſſe againſt them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A pretye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to bring one to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell.</note>Ye hit partelye the maſſe on the heade. But ye knowe what remedie they haue in theyr canon lawes.</p>
               <q>Si non caſte tamen caute.</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>That is as muche to ſaye, yf thou canſte not liue chaſtelye, playe thou the knaue pryuelye. But to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: The ſeconde poynte, that wee ſhall marke in Paules wordes, is that he doeth preferre, the honeſte companiynge together of man and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6563:47"/> wyfe in Matrimonye, before faſting or prayer,<note place="margin">Godlye coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle.</note> or before the wyueleſſe life in theim that haue not the gyfte of continencye or chaſtitye. For, he ſayeth: And come agayne together, leſte Sathan do tempte you for your incontinencye, that is to ſaye,<note place="margin">Sometymes the lyberty of Matrimonye is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before prayer and faſtynge.</note> yf ye perceaue, that ye can not lyue chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, during the time of your praiers, leaue prayinge alone: For, then oughte ye to preferre the honeſt ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertye of Matrimony, before prayer, leſte Sathan doe tempte you. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than is a ſubtill and craftye enemie, therefore, ye muſte beware of hym, leſt vnder the ſhadowe and coloure of prayer, he cauſe you to commytte ſome filtheneſſe. Therefore, Saint Paule ſayeth afterwardes: This I ſaye of fauoure and not of commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demente. Where vpon, I dare bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſaye, that youre holye father the Pope is a very Sathan or rather an incarnate deuell,<note place="margin">The Pope is a deuell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate.</note> whyche vnder the pretence &amp; colour of prayer doeth cauſe his prieſts to fal into the net of
<pb facs="tcp:6563:48"/> of the deuyll by manye abhominable and horrible ſynnes. Why wyll the not permit vnto them the ſame, that Sainct Paule doeth bothe permitte and alſo commaunde vnto all thoſe, that want the gyfte of chaſtitie? doth that fleaſhlye Idol thinke, that to be withoute a wyfe,<note place="margin">The true chaſtitye.</note> is to lyue chaſtely? The true chaſtitye doeth conſiſte in the true pureneſſe of the hearte, and minde.<note place="margin">Ambroſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the .vii. Chapter of the firſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Corinth. i. Corinth. vii</note> For as Ambroſe ſayth, what doeth it auayle or profite, if thy body beinge chaſte and cleane, they ſoule or mynde be polluted and defyled? To be ſhorte, no man can be coumpted chaſte before God, except he be holye bothe in bodye, and alſo in ſpiryte.</p>
               <p>Whiche thinge can not be in ſuche pryeſtes, that haue not the gyfte of chaſtitye, vntill they vſe the godlye remedye, that is offered vnto them in the holy eſtate of Matrimonye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>When I doe wel weighe the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Saint Paule, where he ſaith. The ſingle men or women, doe care for the thynges that belonge to the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6563:48"/> lorde, that they may be holy both in body and alſo in ſpirite, I do in a ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner agree to your ſayenges. But go forwardes I pray you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The true Chryſtian.</speaker>
               <p>The thirde doctrine, that we do learne of Paules wordes, is, that there is neyther faſtinge nor prayer,<note place="margin">Neither fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting nor pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er can quench the fier of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie.</note> that can quenche the fyer of inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie, excepte god dothe quenche it him ſelfe, by his eſpeciall grace.</p>
               <p>Whych thynge ſayncte Paule doth well declare when he ſayeth. Come together agayne, leaſte Sathan do tempte you for your incontinencye.<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> Marke ye nowe this: if the inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie could be taken away by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or faſtinges, ſayncte Paule nede not to ſaye: Come together agayne, leaſt for your incontinencie, ye be tempted of Sathan, but rather: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtill in faſting and prayer, and ſo ſhal ye ouercome and quenche at length the burning concupiſcence of your fleſhe. Agayne, he ſayeth not:<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> he that can not abſteyne, let hym praye and faſt, but contrarywyſe he
<pb facs="tcp:6563:49"/> ſayeth:<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> he that hathe not the gifte of chaſtitye let him marrye. Moreouer he doth not write: for auoydynge of fornication, let euery man faſte and praye, or beate him ſelfe, but rather this commaundement doth he geue for auoydinge of fornication, let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye man haue his wife, and euerye woman haue her huſbande. I do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes excepte theym,<note place="margin">Who they be that ought to be accepted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this lawe</note> that do not tempte God, that is to ſaye, whyche can not commodiouſly come at their wiues, by reaſon of theyr office or vocation, as manye gentlemen and other be, whych by the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of theyr prynce, are fayne to kepe the warres or marchaundiſe, folowinge theyr marchaundiſe and other like.<note place="margin">They that cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modyouſelye come at theyr owne wyues ought to pray for the gyft of chaſtytye.</note> Suche are bound to pray vnto almightye god, that he vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to geue them the gifte of chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie duryng the time that they be ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent from tdeyr wiues: but yet they ought not to ſeparate them ſelues, for to longe a time, nor withoute a iuſt and lawefull cauſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:6563:49"/>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Why doth ſainet Paule wryte then that it is good for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to touche a woman?<note place="margin">The fift ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumente of the papyſte of oure tyme. i. Cor. vii.</note> Here ſaint Paule ſemeth to alowe the opinion of theym that ſaye, that it is meritorious or auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable vnto ſaluation to liue without the companye of a woman, or in the ſtate of ſingle life.<note place="margin">Math. xix.</note> Doth not alſo our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte ſay him ſelfe, that there be ſome, whyche haue made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues chaſte for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauens ſake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>The true Chryſtian.</speaker>
               <p>All theſe places make nothyng for the papiſtes. For firſt and foremoſt,<note place="margin">Aunſwere. Howe the wordes of ſainte Paule oughte to be vnderſtanded</note> the meaning of ſainct Paule, is not, that to abſteyne from a woman, is meritorious, or auaileable vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, but that it is more commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious for a man, if he can liue ſo, or hath the gifte of chaſtitie, to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maryed, then to be maryed.</p>
               <p>For,<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> he that is ſingle and vnmaried hauing the gifte of chaſtity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencie, careth for the thinges that
<pb facs="tcp:6563:50"/> perteyne vnto the lord, that he maye be holy both in body, and alſo in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite: he maye at all times go abrode to preache the goſpell,<note place="margin">Math. x.</note> and if perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth ariſe for the wordes ſake, he ſhall neyther by wife nor by chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be letted to flye from citye to citye, as our ſauiour Ieſus Chryſte doth byd: and if he fall into the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies handes, he ſhall with a better minde go to the fyer. Manye other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities might I rehearce, which they haue, that hauinge the gyfte of chaſtitie do remaine vnmaried. But what dothe this pertayne to youre wiueleſſe prieſtes,<note place="margin">The ſayenge of ſaint paule doth nothyng pertayne to the papiſtes.</note> which as vile ſtin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king goates do walowe them ſelues in all kinde of Sodomie and whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? They ſay that it is not lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for them to haue wiues of theyr owne, and to touche theym, as God hathe ordeyned and appoynted, but how they handle other mens wiues &amp; commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> harlots in their blind and theuiſhe corners,<note place="margin">Roma. i.</note> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> very childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſtreete are able to teſtifye. Theſe are they, that for the deſpiſing of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6563:50"/> lordes inſtitutution and ordinaunce are geuen vp into a reprobate ſence that they ſhuld do the things which are both vnſemely &amp; alo too filthye,<note place="margin">Math. xix.</note> &amp; abhominable to be vttered out. As for the wordes of our ſauioure Ieſu Chriſt, they are eaſy to be vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded: for, there he ſpeaketh of thoſe, that hauing receiued the gift of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie, do abſteyne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mariage, that they maye the better ſpreade abrode and publiſhe, the glad and ioyfull ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges of the kingedome of heauen. But how chaſtelye doth your wyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe marchants liue, I beſeche you? Can any man ſay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues chaſte,<note place="margin">They be as chaſte as ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes or as are luſty ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>launtes that runne among mares.</note> or that they haue gelded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. Let the pore women and maydens, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſeduce &amp; deceiue dayly, teſtify of the ſame. And as for the preachings of the goſpel of god, which our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus chriſt doth call therin that place the kingdome of heauen, that is not the marke that they ſhot at, in abſteining fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mariage, but that they maye liue at eaſe, &amp; pamper vp
<pb facs="tcp:6563:51"/> vp their idell and reſtye bodies, that ſo they may do the better ſeruice vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lady Venus at all times,<note place="margin">Naye not ſo, for they be oure Ladyes knyghtes</note> whoſe knightes they do declare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be. This am I ſure of, that there haue bene more godly ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s made here in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in a weke, by honeſt maried miniſters, that liued in the feare of god, in the holy eſtate of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimonye, then be nowe made in a hole yeare, by your mayden prieſtes and luſty cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pions of dame Venus.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
                  </label> How can ye proue, that they, which make theym ſelues chaſte, or gelde theym ſelues for the kingedome of heauens ſake, haue receyued the gift of chaſtity before?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>When the apoſtles had ſayde if ſhe matter be ſo betwixte the man &amp; the wife,<note place="margin">Aunſwere. Math. xix.</note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is not good to mary, our ſauiour Ieſus chriſt did aunſwere &amp; ſay: Al men be not able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend or receiue this ſayenge, but they to whom it is geuen. Nowe if ye will aſke me who they be, that geld them ſelues or that make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues chaſte
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6563:51"/> for the kingdome of heauens ſake: I wil aunſwere,<note place="margin">They do geld them ſelues for the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens ſake, to whome it is geuen.</note> that they gelde them ſelues or make theym ſelues chaſte for the kingedome of heauens ſake, vnto whom it is geuen. But thys (as I haue ſayde before) can not be ſpoken of your vnmaried and wiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſhauelinges, for they neyther liue chaſtely, nor yet care for the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moting or ſetting forth of the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, but to ſet out theyr owne kingdome &amp; glory, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may liue like lordes &amp; kinges and haue al mens heads vnder their girdelles. Nowe do ye plainely ſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the places that ye haue alleadged, do no more pertaine vnto your holy prieſts than the godly documentes of virginitie,<note place="margin">i. Corin. vii.</note> that ſ. Paule geueth in the epiſtel to the Corinthians, do pertaine, to the hores of the ſtewes.<note place="margin">Wolde God ſuche a lawe myght be made.</note> If kinges and princes woulde once make a lawe, that al prieſtes that be found to liue vnchaſtely, or to lead an vncleane &amp; filthy life, ſhould be bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vp as they make lawes to burne them vp, that would fayne liue in the feare of god,
<pb facs="tcp:6563:52"/> and kepe them ſelues vndefiled me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſte, ye ſhould ſe ſhortly theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon bulles to ſing an other ſong: But as longe as they maye without anye feare of punihſement walowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in euery mans bedde, &amp; haue gentilwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with freeh hoodes (for ſo make they theyr boaſtes) to come home to them into their owne cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, they wil be ſtill at defiaunce with matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. And no meruaile why? For as long as they may haue their wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues &amp; children ſitting by other mens fiers,<note place="margin">But this wiſedome of theirs ſhalbe derely ſolde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at length.</note> and to be kepte at other mens coſtes &amp; charges, they were fooles (ſith that they be at this poynt, that they thinke that there is neither hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen nor hell) if they woulde burden them ſelues with the charges, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, &amp; cares that do pertaine to the holy eſtate of matrimony. But, alas what ſhal be the ende of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? As ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable whoremongers &amp; adulte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rers, &amp; as ſtinking &amp; filthy Sodomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, they ſhall be caſte into the lake that burneth with fire &amp; brimſtone,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:6563:52"/>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>I perceaue that ſwete meate muſt haue ſoure ſawce.<note place="margin">The ſyxte argument of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes of oure time.</note> They ſayd more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, that the pryeſtes, whyche dyd mary in kyng Edwardes dayes, did ſinne moſte greuouſly againſte god, and not onely againſt the lawes and conſtitucions of our holy mother the churche, becauſe that they dyd moſte vngodly breake the vowes, whyche they made vnto god. For, ſaye they, if we ſhoulde but make a faythfull promiſe vnto a mortall man, it were a ſhame for vs to breake it: What ought we then to iudge of thoſe that dare moſte vngodlye preſume, to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eake the vowes or promiſſes, that they haue made ſolemnely vnto god,<note place="margin">The thunder boltes of the Papyſtes,</note> before his holy churche? They there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that marrye, after they haue made theyr vowe, doe not onely liue in adultery, but alſo are vnfaythfull promiſſe breakers. And they that are ſuche muſte nedes prouoke the wrath and indignation of God, not onelye againſt them ſelues, but alſo againſt the contrye that they dwel in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:53"/>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aunſwere. Of vowes.</note>Or euer we doe preceade any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we muſte marke what a vowe is? Secondly what thinges ought to be conſydered in makyng of a vowe. Fyrſte and foremoſte, it is agreed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all men, that the ſame, which we call a promyſſe, in the reſpecte of men, is called a vowe in the reſpecte of god.<note place="margin">what a vowe is.</note> But this ye wil graunte me, that we be wonte to promyſſe thoſe thinges vnto men, whiche we know to be acceptable vnto them, elles our promiſſe ſhal ſkarcely be welcome, it ſhal ſkarcelye be alowed or accepted of them, to whom it is made. Howe muche more oughte we to beware, tht we promyſſe or vowe nothinge vnto God, excepte we knowe by hys word, that it is acceptable vnto him for,<note place="margin">Leui. x.</note> he doth deteſtand abhorre al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of worſhippinges and ſeruyces, that he him ſelfe hath not preſcribed in his holy and ſacred word.<note place="margin">Eſaye. xix, Math. xv.</note> And for this cauſe he cryeth oute by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſaiynge: they worſhyppe me in vaine, teachyng the doctrines &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6563:53"/> of men. Therfore, in making of a vowe,<note place="margin">Howe manye thynges are to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of a vowe.</note> thre things are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered: what he is vnto whome we make the vowe: what we be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> make the vowe, and for what intent or in what reſpect we do make it. Firſte &amp; formoſt, then, we muſt conſider with our ſelues, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is god, vnto whome, we make our vowe, which as I ſaid before, can awaye wyth no ſeruice, worſhippinge or religion, that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented or found out by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without or againſt his holy word, thoughe in the ſight, of the foolyſhe world, it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth neuer ſo gay, excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; goodly. If the thyng then,<note place="margin">The thynge that we vow vnto god, muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded in gods booke or elles oure vowe is abho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynable.</note> that we promyſſe or vow vnto him be not commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded or preſcribed vnto vs in his word, it muſte nedes ſtinke before the face of his maieſtye: yea in ſtede of prayſe or reward we ſhal receaue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>digne pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, for oure abomynable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, &amp; vnaduiſed raſhnes. God doth only require of vs an obedience towardes his holy law,<note place="margin">What God doeth requyre of vs.</note> inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; ordenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, which if we do offer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him through faith in oure ſauioure Ieſu chriſt, though on oure part it be
<pb facs="tcp:6563:54"/> moſte vnperfecte, yet wyl he accepte it for his ſonne Ieſu Chriſtes ſake, and impute it vnto vs, as moſte per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte. But if leauynge the ſame obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyence, that we owe vnto hys holye lawe, inſtitutions and ordinaunces, we doe ſeke newe waies for to ſerue and worſhyppe hym, doubteleſſe, he wyl poure the ſame vengeaunce vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs,<note place="margin">Leui. x. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> xv.</note> that he dyd poure vpon Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab and Abihu and alſo vpon Saul, the firſt kyng of the Iſraelites.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>I do remember well, how ſore god dyd punyſhe them. For Nadab, and Abihu were before the whole congre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation of Iſrael deuoured with fier, that came downe from the wrathe and indignation of God. And as for Saull both his kyngdome was rent from him, and alſo he him ſelfe, was delyuered vp vnto an vncleane ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, whych ſhould vexe and torment hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Bleſſed are ye, neighbour, yf theſe mens harmes and greuous punyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6563:54"/> can make you to beware. But now, wyll I come to the ſecond thinge, that oughte to be conſydered in making of a vowe. When we go about to promiſſe or vowe any thing vnto almyghtye God, we muſte not onelye conſyder, that it is God vnto whom we make the vowe, but alſo what we are oure ſelues, that doe make it. We muſt alwaies haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, that of oure ſelues we can doe nothinge. Therefore, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſe a thing, that it lieth not in vs,<note place="margin">We muſte vow nothing that it lyeth not in vs to perfourme, and whereof we haue no promiſſe in gods boke.</note> to perfourme, and whereof we haue no promyſſe in Gods booke that we ſhal obteine it at gods handes (if we do aſke it) it is a paryllous preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and whyche deſerueth no ſmall confuſyon and ſhame bothe before god and the worlde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>By your ſaiynge, all that we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſe and vowe in oure baptiſme, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> it is but a paryllous preſumption.<note place="margin">What we doe promyſſe and vowe in baptiſme.</note> For it lyeth not is vs, to forſake the diuel and his works, the pompes and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of this wycked world, nor yet
<pb facs="tcp:6563:55"/> the ſinful luſtes of the fleſh. We can not of our ſelues beleue all the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the chriſten faithe, with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges, that we are commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded to beleue in gods worde. It lieth in no mans power to walcke all the daies of his lyfe in gods holy lawe &amp; commaundements. And yet all theſe things, we do promiſſe and vowe in our baptiſme. Therefore, might any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hearing you ſpeake thus, accuſe vs al, of preſumption and raſhenes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aunſwere. God doeth promyſe all thoſe thinges that we doe vowe and promyſſe in baptiſme, and therfore are we ſure that we ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne them at his handes by faythful prayers.</note>But ye muſt marke good neighbour that god doth in his holy worde, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre of vs all thoſe thinges, that ye haue reherced, and which we do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſe &amp; vowe in our baptiſme. For, his wyl &amp; pleaſure is, that we ſhould forſake the deuil &amp; hys workes, that we ſhoulde be at defiaunce wyth the pompes and vanities of the wycked world, and wyth the ſinnefull luſtes of our fleſh. His wil and pleaſure is, that we ſhould beleue and credite all thinges, that he doth ſet forthe vnto vs in his word, takinge a ſure holde through faith vpon his mercy &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6563:55"/> declared vnto vs in hys Sonne Ieſu chriſt, our lord &amp; ſauiour, &amp; that all the daies of our life, we ſhold en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour our ſelues to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vttermoſte of our power, to walke ſincerely in hys holy lawes and commaundements. Therfore we may be ſure, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll at al times (if we do require it of him with faithful praiers) aſſiſte vs with his grace, that we may to his glory &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our owne ſoules per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, &amp; fulfil al thoſe godly promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and vowes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue made vnto him in oure baptiſme, wherein we haue ſo faythfullye and ſo ſtreightly bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d oure ſelues vnto him, &amp; his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are no more our owne me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For, why?<note place="margin">In baptyſme we doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts of the lorde, ſo that we are no more our owne men.</note> by receauing this holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of baptiſme, which is a ſeale of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; promiſſes of god, we doe acknowledge &amp; confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are bought &amp; purchaſed vnto hym, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moſt dere &amp; precious blod of his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ieſu chriſt our lord: what preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption is it then, ſith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are no more oure owne me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of him, that hathe ſo derelye boughte vs, whiche thing as I ſaid before we do acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb facs="tcp:6563:56"/> by takynge vpon vs the ſeate of the people of God: what preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I ſaye, is it for vs, to promyſſe or enterpriſe anye thinge, wythoute the knowledge, wyll and pleaſure of oure ſoueraine lord and maſter? But where haue we anye place, yea, one iote or ſillable in all the whole bodie of the ſcriptures, that doeth certifye vs, that it is the wyl and pleaſure of god (who is oure ſouerayne lord and Maſter) that we ſhold vowe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſe to liue a ſingle and wyue leſſe lyfe, as longe as we haue any breath in oure bodyes?<note place="margin">The cruel tyranny of the preachers of oure tyme.</note> It is manyfeſt then that all thoſe godlye vowes, that ye doe ſo magnifye &amp; extolle, and which youre Preachers doe defende wyth tothe and nayle, perſecutyng them, moſt tyrannouſly and alſo moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellye, that perceauynge the erroure and parall that they be in, do with a good and vpright conſcience, beynge builded in gods worde, vtterlye for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake, and abiure them, it is moſte manyfeſt I ſaye, that ſuche vowes, are wythoute faythe, ſythe that they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6563:56"/> haue no grounde nor foundation in goddes holy worde. Therfore, away with them, for what can they be els but ſinne. Whatſoeuer ſayth ſaynct Paule is not of faythe,<note place="margin">Roma. xiiii. Hebr. xii.</note> the ſame is ſinne. Againe: withoute faythe, it is impoſſible for to pleaſe god. We mighte ſaye then, and that by good right, that they whiche are offended with them, that being better inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in goddes lawe, do go from ſuch raſhe &amp; preſumptuous vowes,<note place="margin">The one ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with as good reaſon as the other.</note> and are at defiaunce with theym, maye with as good a cauſe be angrye and diſpleaſed with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that do flye and forſake ſinne, or that will to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of theyr power, auoyde and eſchewe thoſe thinges, whyche they knowe to be abhominable and ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king before the face of almighty god Why are they ſo blinded, that they will not ſee this canon of theyrs:<note place="margin">Iſidorus in ſinonimis li. 23. queſtione 4. capi. In male pro.</note>
                  <q>In male promiſſis reſcinde fidem: in turpi voto muta decretum: quod incaute vouiſti, ne facias, impia eſt promiſſio, quaeſcelere adimpletur.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That is to ſay: In thoſe things that be not wel promiſed, breake thou thi
<pb facs="tcp:6563:57"/> promiſſe. In a ſhamefull &amp; vnhoneſt vowe chaung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy mind: Do not the thing,<note place="margin">An applienge of the canon vnto the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent matter.</note> that thou haſt vowed vnware or without deliberation &amp; aduiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t It is an vngodly promiſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is fulfil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, with wickedneſſe. Nowe can ye ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the promiſſe of your wiue leſſe prieſts, is good, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is well made, ſith that it is without faythe, &amp; hath no maner of ground in gods booke? why ſhould they not then by the ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of this canon breake it? Agayne, howe ſhameful &amp; vnhoneſt the vowe that they make is, it is apparaunt to the ſight of all men. For by it they are conſtreined to forſake the honeſt &amp; lawful remedye, that god hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for all men, &amp; for lacke of it, to walow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in al kind of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy &amp; ſtinking abhomination. Why do they not then (as this holy decree doth bid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) chaunge their minde, &amp; that betimes, leſt for their ſtinking &amp; filthy abomination, they be vtterly caſt out of the fauour &amp; ſighte of god. Thirdly, the vow y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they make, they make it ſo vnaduiſedly, &amp; without al deliberation, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many prieſts can not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6563:57"/> tel whether thei euer made any vow or not. And as for your friers,<note place="margin">Al ſeculare prieſtes that I haue tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wythall haue ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmed vnto me, that they neuer made vowes ſauing onely that when the Byſhop gaue them the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ote, he dyd ſay: Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe iugum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitatis. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue thou the yoke of chaſtitye.</note> nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; monks, they be faine to make their vowes, afore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they knowe the bente of their owne bowe, that is to ſaye, afore that they haue examined &amp; tried their owne ſtrength, or what they be able, to abide or do. Shal we ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch vowes are aduiſedly done &amp; with ſuch a deliberation, as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in ſo high a matter, as this is They may then by the auctority and vertue of their holy canones breake ſuch vnaduiſed vowes. For, beſides the afore rehearced canone, theſe are the wordes of the bleſſed martir S. Ciprian: If the virgins y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue with fayth vowed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues vnto Chriſt,<note place="margin">Cipri. li. 1. epiſtolarum epiſtola. 2.</note> can not perſeuer or will not: it is bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they mary tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they ſhould through their tender niceneſſe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſneſſe fal into the fier.<note place="margin">Augu. in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro de bono coniug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>li ad Iulianum. diſci. 27. capi. Quondam.</note> And S. Auguſtine doth alowe the mariage of ſuch, inuehing ſharpelye agaynſt them, that cal ſuch mariage, aduou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and go about to ſeparate them, that do mary after theyr vowe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:58"/>
               <p>The wordes are theſe: Some do ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe, that they that mary after theyr vowe, are adulterers, but I ſaye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that they whiche ſeparate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do offend greuouſly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> I praye you, geue me a litell leaue to ſpeake: if nowe your wife, that is wedded vnto you by the lawes of god and of the realme, ſhuld in your life time, go take another huſbande would not all the worlde counte her an adultereſſe? What ought then to be ſayd of thoſe women, that beyng wedded vnto Chriſte by a ſolemne promiſſe or vowe, be not affrayed theyr huſbande being aliue, to take mortall and ſinnefull men to theyr huſbandes. The like may be ſayd of the men, whether they be ſeculare prieſtes or other, for, as they ſaye, they be al maried vnto our lady, and vnto our mother the holy church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>It is not for nought that ſainct Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine doth both write and ſay,<note place="margin">Aunſwere.</note> that they, which iudge or coumpte thoſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6563:58"/> perſons,<note place="margin">Auguſt. 27. queſtio. 1. cap. nuptia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> whiche marye after theyr vowe, to be adulterers, are ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye deceyued by a fooliſhe ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, meaning the ſelfe ſame ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude that ye haue nowe aledged and brought in. Ye ſhal then vnderſtand that we are al both men and wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as many as do pertaine to the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt of life, maried vnto the lorde. For,<note place="margin">Oſee. ii.</note> thus he ſayeth him ſelfe vnto his faythful congregation &amp; church: I will mary the vnto me in fayth.</p>
               <p>Againe, bee not theſe the wordes of ſayncte Paule,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. xi.</note> I haue coupled you (ſpeaking to the hole churche of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus) to one man, to make you a chaſte virgin to Chriſte. In howe many places, is the faythfull congre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation or churche, called the ſpouſe and wiſe of the lambe? Ye learne by this, that we are al,<note place="margin">Reuela. xix. Epheſi. v.</note> as manye as do beleue and put our truſt in the euer-liuing and eternal god, the ſpouſe of our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſte. Therefore we nede not to be maried or wedded to him, by ſuche kinde of newe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vowes, ſith that we are already
<pb facs="tcp:6563:59"/> through faythe, whereby we do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend and take holde vpon the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunte that God hathe made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twyxt him and vs, ſo ſurelye maried to him,<note place="margin">Ephe. v.</note> being in manye and ſondrye places of the ſcriptures called the ſpouſe &amp; wife of the lambe, I meane of the onely begotten ſonne of God, our ſauiour Ieſu Chryſte, who hath ſo loued vs, that he gaue him ſelfe for vs, to ſanctifye and clenſe vs, in the fountayne of water, through the word, to make vs to him ſelfe a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious congregation, without ſpotte or wrinkle, or any ſuch thinge, that ſo we mighte be holye and wythout blame. To tell you the truth, it is ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to be beleued, that by ſuch inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vowes (whych we may well call doctrines of deuels) we are vtterlye ſeparated and diuorſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our true huſbande our ſauiour Ieſu Chryſte,<note place="margin">By popiſhe vowes, we are ſeparated and diuorſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our true huſband our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt.</note> and coupled or maried vnto Idolles I meane vnto deade creatures, whych we knowe not whether they be in heauen or in hell. For by them ſome be maried to Frauncys, ſome
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6563:59"/> to Dominike, ſome to Auguſtine, and ſome to this or that ſayncte (at leaſt they call theym ſo) and ſo poore Chriſt, the only huſband of the true chriſtian church, is vtterly forſaken and not once thought vpon. All ye then, that throughe ignoraunce and errour, haue coupled your ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch vnlawefull huſbandes, with whom ye do dayly and hourely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſpirituall whoredome (whyche is the mother and nurce of al filthye and ſtinkyng abhomination whiche is committed in the bodye to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter caſtyng away of the ſoule)<note place="margin">Spirituall whoredome is mother and nurce of all filthye and ſtinking abho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mination. Rom. i.</note> repent betimes and come agayne to youre true and lawefull huſbande, our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſu Chriſte, and ſtycke to his lawes, whereby he hathe ordeyned and appoynted,<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> that for auoydinge of whoredome, euerye man ſhoulde haue his wyfe, and euerye woman, her huſbande. Let it not moue you, that ye haue made a promiſſe, ſyth that it was made vnaduiſedlye and wythoute deliberation, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſith that it can not be fulfilled
<pb facs="tcp:6563:60"/> without committing great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and miſchiefe. For as ye learn by the canone heretofore alledged &amp; rehearced, ſuch a promiſſe is vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ought in no wiſe to be kept. It is not vnknowen, that many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence and coloure of ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of their vowes, or becauſe that they would not ſeme to breake them haue committed moſt ſhamefull and horrible murthers. We do reade in a certayne epiſtell that a famous clerke called Huldarichus,<note place="margin">Huldaricus ad Nicolaum papam.</note> beynge then byſhop of Auguſt, did write vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Pope Nicolas being firſte of that name, that Gregorye did on a tyme cauſe one of his ponds to be drawen and that there was founde in it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue ſixe thouſand heades of yonge infantes which had bene murthered &amp; caſt into it,<note place="margin">A notable hiſtorie.</note> by thoſe, that by theyr violent and tirannous lawes, were forbidden to marye.<note place="margin">The repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce and ſobbing of Gregory.</note> Whiche when Gregory did ſee being wonderfullie moued in his mind did with ſighing and ſobbinge praiſe and commende
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6563:60"/> highly the ſayinge of Sainct Paule,<note place="margin">1. Cor. vii.</note> where he writeth and ſayth: Better it is to marry than to burne, addyng vnto it: yea, better it is to marrye, and to ſuffer to marry, than to geue occaſyon of ſuch a ſhameful murther and chyldren ſlaughter. Thys was done in Gregories time, many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth yeares ago: What, thinke ye, hath bene done ſence, among ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye thouſand of Nonnes and friers, whyche are ſpreade abrode throughe oute all the hole worlde? I doe here. Let paſſe the Sodoniticall and filthy actes, that theſe marked mounſters of Antichriſte doe perpretrate and committe amonge them ſelues, yf they chaunce to want and lacke wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: And all this doe they forſothe, that they maye ſeme vnto men to kepe the promyſſe &amp; vowe that they haue made. But, as Iſidorus ſaieth,<note place="margin">What an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly promiſe is.</note> vngodly is that promiſſe, that is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled with ſuch wickednes and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe. Therefore, moſte derely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued bretherne and ſyſters in Chryſte breake ſuch dyueliſhe promyſſes and
<pb facs="tcp:6563:61"/> vowes betimes, &amp; come awaye from that whoryſh and bloudy generation vnto your true and lawful huſbande our ſauiour Ieſu Chryſt: &amp; if ye haue not the gifte of chaſtitie, couple your ſelues in honeſt Matrimony, hauing the feare of God before youre eyes, that ye may kepe your ſelues vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led members of oure Sauioure Ieſu Chryſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>I am ſory that I haue brought you ſo farre from the mattyer, that ye were in, I am affrayed that ye wyll ſcarcely remember where ye lefte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Take ye no thought for that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member as wel where I lefte, as yf I had made no degreſſion at al. We were in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d point, which I ſaid ought to be conſydered in making of a vow. And in it beſydes that, which hathe bene ſayde alredye, this ought diligentlye to be obſerued &amp; marked: Syth that we are able to do nothing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6563:61"/> of oure ſelues,<note place="margin">We muſte vow nothyng that maye let vs in our vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> &amp; that we be no more our owne me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but are derely bought, we muſte beware that we doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſe or vowe nothinge, that maye be a let or a hyndraunce vnto vs, in that vocation or kynde of lyfe, that it ſhal pleaſe oure ſoueraine Lorde and Maſter to call vs to, as this foolyſhe vowe of ſingle life, is vnto all thoſe, that lacke the gift of chaſtitye. They theyr ſelues can beare recorde, what tormentyng and vexation they feele in the fleſh, ſo that the troubles that are commenlye in wedlocke, are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in comparyſon of it. Can they ſtudy or pray, thinke you? or can they doe anye thynge, that perteyneth to theyr vocation or callyng? God kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, there is a poore ſtudyinge, but a more homelye prayinge, where the fyer of concupiſcence of the fleaſh, is kyndeled, and no laweful water by, for to quenche it. Moreouer, wee muſte in this ſeconde poynte, that perteineth vnto vs beware and take hede, that we do not ſpoile our ſelues of that goodly lybertye and fredome
<pb facs="tcp:6563:62"/> that oure ſauioure Ieſu Chriſt, hath ſo derely bought and pourchaſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, we muſt take hede I ſaye leſte with oure fooliſhe vowes and vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſed promyſſes we doe make oure ſelues bothe ſeruauntes and ſlaues vnto thoſe thynges, that God wyll haue to be ſeruaunts vnto vs. Chriſt our ſauioure wyll haue vs to be free vnto hym,<note place="margin">Chryſt our ſauyour wyll haue vs to be free vnto him</note> and in his fredome to vſe all hys creatures wyth thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge, as he hym ſelfe hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ordeined, let vs beware ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we become not, vnder the ſhadow and coloure of their goodlye vowes, the ſeruaunts of mens drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and traditions. Stand faſt ſaith Saint Paule,<note place="margin">Gala. v.</note> in the libertye where with Chriſt hath made you free, and wrappe not youre ſelues agayne in the yoke of bondage. And after that he had geuen counſell touchinge the wyueleſſe and ſyngle lyfe, he doeth adde by and by theſe wordes. Thys ſpeake I for your profite,<note place="margin">i. Corin. vii.</note> not to tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle you in a ſnare. Who conſidering theſe thynges wolde not iudge them
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6563:62"/> to be ſtarke madde, and beſides theyr owne ſelues, that hauynge ſuche a goodly lybertie and fredome already purchaſſed vnto them, wherein they may moſte conuenyentlye ſerue and worſhyp god, as he hym ſelfe wyl be ſerued and worſhypped, do witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye caſte them ſelues into a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bondage and thraldome, where they ſhalbe fayne, by reaſon of theyr fooliſh and vnaduiſed vowe, to ſerue god, as moſt vngodly, and ſuperſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons ſhall preſcribe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt vnto them, and not as he him ſelfe hathe wylled and ordeyned in hys worde. There againe, ſhall they loſe the free and lawful vſe or hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of the good creatures of God.<note place="margin">What ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and fredom we loſe by popyſh vowes.</note> and thoughe they burne neuer ſo much wyth the fyer of concupiſcence and incontinencye, they ſhall neuer be ſuffered becauſe of theyr wycked bond, to haue acceſſe vnto thoſe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full waters, that God, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnynge hathe appoynted for the quenchynge and puttinge oute of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:63"/>
               <p>But what remedy, when they haue once brought them ſelues, in to that bondage and thraldom: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
                  </label> Is it lawful for them to gette oute of it agayne, or not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Why not? are they not the ſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the lord? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> Who dare kepe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans ſeruaunt agaynſt the wil of hys maſter? Againe, is it not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> know the ſelues to be with wronge Maſters, vnto whome they owe no ſeruyce at all, and alſo to whom they haue bene inticed and broughte by ſottell and deceatefull meanes, for to come agayne vnto theyr ryghte and lawfull maſters, from whome they were intyced and bigged awaye? Chryſt our ſauyoure is oure ſoueraine lord and maſter: If then by the deceauableneſſe of mens doctrines and perſwaſyons,<note place="margin">Math .x.</note> we be made to ſhake of, hys gentle &amp; eaſye yoke, and receaue vpon vs the intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable burdone of mens tradytions &amp; dreames: ſhal it not be lawfull for vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we perceaue our owne folly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6563:63"/> and howe ſhamefully we haue bene begiled, for to come agayne (notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandynge that we did make a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſe vnaduyſedly and wythout de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyberation) vnto our ſouerayne lorde and Maſter, whyche is our ſauyoure Ieſus Chriſt, who in his holy goſpel doeth crye oute and ſaye:<note place="margin">Math. xi.</note> Come vnto me, all ye that laboure and are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and I wyll refreſhe you? Againe: doe ye not thinke it to be lawfull for vs, to flee from ſinne vnto god?<note place="margin">If it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to flee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne it is lawful to flee from popyſh. vowes.</note> But it hath be alredy declared, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that all ſuche vowes, ſithe that they be not of fayth, are but abomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and ſinne before god. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we maye lawfullye and wyth a good &amp; vpright conſcyence, flee from them and forſake them, whatſoeuer the wycked worlde ſayeth to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>There remaineth yet behinde, the third thyng, which ye ſayd, ought to be conſydered in makyng of a vowe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:64"/>
               <p>Ye ſaye very well, and I perceaue that ye are vnwylling, that I ſhould leaue any thinge behynd. The thyrd thing then, whyche ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in making of a vowe is this: When we goe about to promyſſe or vowe any thinge vnto god, we muſt conſyder and weighe wyth oure ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, for what intente or in what reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecte we doe it.<note place="margin">If a vowe be neuer ſo lawfull yet muſt we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyder, for what intente we do marke it.</note> For, it maye be ſo, that beynge done for this or that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente and in this or that reſpecte, it ſhalbe pleaſaunt and acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, where as if it be done for an other intente, or in another reſpect, it ſhall ſtinke before the face of hys maieſtye. As for an exaumple, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue that the drynkyng of wyne, is hurteful vnto me, or that it doeth let and hynder me in my vocation and callynge: Whereby I am moued to abſteine from it altogether: and that I maye haue the better occaſyon to do it, I bind my ſelfe to it by a vowe, promiſyng faythfully vnto god, that I wyl all the dayes of my life (except I be dryuen to doe the contrarye by
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6563:64"/> vrgent neceſſity) refraine from drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of wyne, that I may the better ſerue hym in that ſtate or condytion of life, that it hath pleaſed him to cal me to. This vowe, ſithe that it is made onely to this ende, that I may folowe my vocation the better, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but pleaſe god. But yf I ſhoulde doe it, thinkyng or beyng perſwaded that the abſteinynge from wyne, is merytorious before god, and that by it I ſhall deſerue heauen or the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuenes of my ſynnes, then muſte ſuche a vowe, be abomynable and ſtinkyng before the face of almighty God.<note place="margin">Thoſe things may we onely vowe that be indifferent and that lye in our power</note> The lyke maye be ſayde of all other thinges, that of them ſelues, are indifferent, and lye in our power Now, let vs graunte by waye of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, that the vowe of chaſtytye or ſingle life, is lawful or alowed in the ſcriptures and worde of god: yet oneleſſe we doe take vppon vs that vowe, to the intent that we may the better geue our ſelfes to the true me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditacion of heauenly thinges, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to this ende that we maye the
<pb facs="tcp:6563:65"/> better edefye the holye congregation and churche of chriſte, by publiſhing and preachinge abrode the glad and ioyfull tidinges of ſaluation, al that we do is abominable in the ſyght of god. For, if we do it, thinking to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue heauen by it, or to this ende that we may liue at eaſe, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ſollicitude and care, or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of this world. And alſo becauſe that we will not be burdoned wyth the charges that pertaine to the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon wealthe: althoughe we coulde liue as chaſte a life, as euer the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed virgin Marye, the mother of our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt did, it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for vs to pleaſe god: all that we do (ſith that in it we do not ſeeke his glorye, and the profyte of our neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour) wil he deteſte and abhorre.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. v. Whye wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes were receyued into the church.</note>And as it is of men, ſo it is of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. It appeareth by the wordes of ſ. Paule, that widowes did promiſſe their ſeruice vnto the church, to this ende, that they might ſe to the poore which were kept at the coſtes &amp; char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of the faythfull congregation &amp;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6563:65"/> in dede they were moſt mete for that purpoſe, for to ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be waſhed &amp; kept cleane, &amp; for to ſee their meate to be handeſomly dreſſed. Howebeit ſaint Paule wil haue none to be cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen to that office vnder thre ſcore yea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res of age, biddinge the yonger wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes to marie &amp; to bring forth chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. As for maidens &amp; virgins, that be endued from aboue with the gift of chaſtity, the chiefe cauſe why.<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> S. Paule will haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to abſteyne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mariage, is, that being free from the cares &amp; troubles that be commonlye in matrimony, they ſhould geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to the contemplation and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of heauenly thinges, &amp; alſo ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour them ſelues by dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reading and hearinge of the ſcriptures, to be holy both in body and alſo in ſpyrite. It appeareth by ſayncte Hieromes writinges, that there were both wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and maydens in his time, which did with the ſubſtaunce that was lefte vnto theym, eyther by theyr huſbandes, or elles by theyr parentes and fryendes, relyue the
<pb facs="tcp:6563:66"/> poore,<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> and alſo maynteyne learning if then, eyther widowes or maidens (I do here ſpeake onely of thoſe that haue the gift of chaſtitye) do abſteine from mariage, for any other intent, or in any other reſpect, than I haue ſayde already: that is to ſaye, if they do thinke, that by ſuch kinde of life, they ſhall merite or deſerue heauen, or do embrace it, to this ende, that they may be free and exempte from all ſorowes and paynes that other women ſuffer in bearyng and bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge vp of theyr children, all that they do is noughte,<note place="margin">God will haue al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to his glory, and to the profyte of our neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</note> and hated of God, who will haue all thinges to be done to his glorye onelye, and for the profite of our neyghboure. Ye may nowe learne by this, howe plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaunte and acceptable the vowes of your prieſtes, Nonnes, freeres, and Monkes, are vnto god. For do they not all, take this vowe of ſingle life or chaſtitye vpon them (though they be as farre from keping of it, as the Eaſt is from the Weſt) to this ende that they maye liue at eaſe, and be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6563:66"/> withoute all troubles and cares of this common life, pamperinge vp or fattinge theym ſelues, wyth the ſweate of other mens browes?</p>
               <p>Agayne, do they it not to this ende, that they maye be in eſtimation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge men, and taken as Goddes, reckeninge holy matrimonie, which hath bene inſtituted of the lord him ſelfe, to be but filthines and pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in compariſon of theyr counter fayted chaſtitye? Yea, they that are of the beſte ſorte amonge theym, do thinke verely that god is greatly in theyr debte, becauſe that they do wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lingly abſteine from this holy eſtate of matrimonye, yea, if God do not place them in his kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, farre aboue his maried electe and choſen, they are readye to enter an action in the lawe agaynſte him. Therfore, we maye well conclude, that all theyr vowes that they make after the rules &amp; doctrines of men,<note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of vowes</note> without or agaynſt gods word, or to ani other ende tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to ſet forth the glory of god &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> profite of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb facs="tcp:6563:67"/> are ſtinking and abhominable before the face of almighty god, and that therefore it is lawefull for anye man or woman, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by the meanes of theym, hath bene broughte into the ſnare of the enemy, for to breake and forſake theym, and if they can not liue chaſte, to couple theym ſelues in honeſt matrimony.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">Deu. xxiii.</note>Yet this ſhall ye finde writen in the ſcriptures: When thou doſt make a vowe vnto the lorde thy god, do not deferre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> day to daye to perfourme it.<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes or the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. ca. v.</note> For verelye the lorde ſhall require it at thy hande. The lyke ſhall ye reade in Eccleſiaſtes otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the preacher, yea ſayeth Moſes yf anye thinge be come forthe of thy lippes, ſee that thou doeſt kepe and perfourme it: as thou haſte vowed vnto the lorde thy god of thine owne free will, and as thou haſte ſpoken wyth thy mouth. What are all men able to ſaye agaynſt ſuche manifeſte and playne textes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:6563:67"/>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>This are al the godly able to ſay,<note place="margin">Aunſwere. Wherin the vowes of the olde lawe dyd conſiſt.</note> that bothe Moſes and Salomon, do ſpeake of the vowes of the olde lawe whych did conſyſt in certayne kinde of ſacrafices, and ceremonies which our ſauiour Ieſus Chryſte did vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye abolyſhe and put downe by his comminge, ſo that they pertayne no more vnto vs, except ye wil haue all other ſacrifices and ceremonyes to pertayne vnto vs alſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe be alſo the wordes of the pſalmiſte. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> Offer thou the ſacrafice of laude and praiſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> &amp; pay thy vowes vnto the higheſt. Againe: make vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, and paye theym vnto the lorde your God. Wil ye ſaye nowe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.</note> that Dauid doth here ſpeak of the vowes of the olde lawe alſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>I will here brynge nothynge of mine owne. Fyrſte,<note place="margin">Aunſwere. Arnobius in pſalm. 50.</note> ye ſhall heare olde father Arnobius, who expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt verſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue alledged writeth on this maner. What ſhalt
<pb facs="tcp:6563:68"/> thou retche vnto me of thine owne? This is thine owne, if thou doeſt with a pure hearte poure before me prayſes and laudes: and paye vnto me to vowe, that thou haſte made me in baptiſme, wherein thou didſt promiſſe that thou wouldeſt forſake the deuel,<note place="margin">God doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire none other vowe of vs, but that which we haue made in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</note> and kepe my commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. Here do we learne by this moſt auncient writer that the vow, which god doth nowe requyre at our handes, is the promiſſe &amp; vowe that we haue made vnto him in baptiſm which we ought as long as we haue anye breathe in our bodies, to ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour our ſelues alwaies to perform and fulfil to the vttermoſt of our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.<note place="margin">Marcus An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tonius Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius in pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>almum. 50</note> Al we (ſaith Marcus Antonius Flaminius writinge vpon the ſame verſe) that profeſſe godlineſſe, do pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſe &amp; vow that we wil preferre the glory of god before al thinges, &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip purely &amp; ſincerely,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in pſal. 55.</note> his holi &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed name. As for the ſecond ſentence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue alledged, thus doth ſ. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine expound it: What ſhould ye vowe or pay? The brute beaſtes that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6563:68"/> were ſomtimes offred at the altare? Offer thou no ſuche thing: thou haſt that thynge in thee, whyche thou mayeſt bothe vowe and paye. Bring forthe of the cheſte of thy hearte, the ſwete ſmelle of laude and prayſe, brynge forth of the cellar of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcyence the ſacrifice of faythe. And whatſoeuer thou doeſt brynge forth, fyre it with charitye. Now do ye ſee, how thoſe holy aunciente doctours, doe expound the places, that ye haue aleaged out of Dauyd, and how that thoſe textes do make nothing at all, for the maynteynynge of the newe fourged vowes of youre wyueleſſe cleargye.<note place="margin">The ende of vowes.</note> Therefore I ſay boldlye in the Lorde, that all ſuche beggerlye vowes notwithſtandyng bothe men and women, that haue bene or are yet entangled wyth them, may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully marry, if they haue not the gift of chaſtetye geuen them: &amp; that none wyl finde faute wyth theyr doinges, excepte it be they, that for the deſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge of gods holye lawe and ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, are alredye geuen ouer into
<pb facs="tcp:6563:69"/> a reprobate ſenſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
                  </label> What ſcriptures, I pray you, can ye bring, that prieſtes ought to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye? Or what example haue they in all the booke of God, otherwyſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Byble, that they ſhould haue wyues?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>We haue examples enoughe. For fyrſt and foremoſt, all the pryeſtes of the olde lawe were maryed. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">The pryeſtes of the old law were maryed</note> Which thinge ye haue graunted me alredye before, excepte ye haue forgotten it. And in the newe Teſtament Chriſt oure Sauiour, dyd call maried men, for to be hys Apoſtels,<note place="margin">Chryſt called maryed men to be hys apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelles.</note> which thinge the heauenly wiſedom of the father, wold not haue done, if it had not ben lawful for his miniſters to marry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> But they dyd put awaye theyr wyues or at leſte theyd dyd ſeparate them ſelues from them, as ſone as they were called.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:6563:69"/>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>It is an eaſye thynge to ſaye ſo, but it is not ſo eaſye to proue it. For yf they had put awaye theyr wyues (as ye ſaye they dyd) then ſhould they haue done contrarye to the doctryne of theyr teacher and Maſter, whyche ſayeth: whome god hathe ioyned and coupled togehter,<note place="margin">Math. xix.</note> let no man put a ſunder. Againe: It is not lawfull for any man to put awaye hys wyfe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte it be for fornication. Moreouer if the Apoſtels had put awaye theyr wyues, wyth what face, I beſeche you, ſhould they haue gone about to teache maryed men how they ought to behaue them ſelues towards their yoke felowes? Amonge all other the bleſſed Apoſtel Saynct Peter ſayth: Lykewyſe, ye men, dwel wyth your wyues accordyng to knowledge,<note place="margin">i. Peter. iii.</note> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge honour vnto the wyfe, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the weaker veſſell, and as vnto them that are heyres alſo of the grace of lyfe, that youre prayers be not hindered. When bothe Peter,
<pb facs="tcp:6563:70"/> and the other Apoſtels alſo, ſhoulde haue geuen this or other lyke coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell vnto maryed men,<note place="margin">What maried men might haue ſayd to the apoſtels if they had forſaken their wyues.</note> myghte they not by good ryghte haue ſayde vnto them agayne: Ah, ye are good felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, ye come to teache vs, howe we ought to behaue our ſelues towards oure wiues, and how that we ought to beare with them, as with the we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker veſſel, to cheriſh and make much of them, yea and that we oughte to loue them, as oure owne fleaſh: how chaunce that we do not the like your ſelues, but put awaye youre owne wyueds from you leſte ye ſhoulde be combred or troubled wyth them, or leſte ye ſhould be fayne to doe, as ye wolde haue vs to doe? Fyrſte, let vs ſee how wel ye agrewith your owne wyues,<note place="margin">Phiſicion heale thy ſelfe</note> or howe ye behaue youre ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues towardes them: and then wyll we folowe the godly counſel, that ye geue vs. Suche lyke tauntes myght maryed men, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were taught theyr duetie towardes theyr wyues, haue geuen to the Apoſtelles, yf it had bene ſo, that they had put away theyr
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6563:70"/> owne wyues, or had ſeperated them ſelues from them. But it is not to be beleued or thought, that the apoſtels wolde geue anye occaſyon, whereby theyr doctrine ſhould be deſpyſed, or lawghed to ſcorne. This then wyth the doctrine of their teacher and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter beynge well conſydered, I maye conclude boldely, that the Apoſtelles dyd not put awaye theyr wyues, nor yet ſeparated them ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Doe we not reade in the ſcriptures, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
                  </label> that the Apoſtelles dyd forſake all thynges, for to folowe our ſauyoure Ieſu chriſt? if they forſoke al thinges be like then they forſoke theyr wiues alſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Who hathe taughte you,<note place="margin">Aunſwere.</note> to make ſuche a goodly argument? I confeſſe it to be true in deede, that when the Apoſtels were called by our ſauyour Ieſu Chryſte, they dyd forſake all thynges, that myghte haue letted them to folowe hym, yea and theyr owne wyues alſo, but not for euer.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:71"/>
               <p>For they ſeparated them ſelues from them only for a time.<note place="margin">A ſimilitude.</note> As when a kynge doeth call hys nobilytye and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munes for to folowe hym in war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, or when he doeth ſende ſome of hys nobles into forrayne countreys for to be hys ambaſſadours there, then doe they all forſake theyr owne buſyneſſe, yea and leaue theyr owne wyues alſo, but not for euer. For they doe it onelye for a tyme, that is to ſaye, tyll theyr Prynce geue them leaue to returne home agayne, or tyl they haue done theyr ambaſſade. Yea ſome of them, yf they perceaue that the time of theyr ambaſſade be ouer longe, doe ſend for they wyues to come vnto them. So the Apoſtels that were marryed, when they could not wythoute leauynge of theyr wyues doe theyr offyce nor folowe theyr vocation,<note place="margin">When the Apoſtels dyd leaue theyr wyues and when they dyd not.</note> they dyd leaue them. But when they coulde doe theyr offyce or folow they vocation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute leauynge of them, truelye they ſeparated not theym ſelues from them. Doe we not reade, that after
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6563:71"/> Saincte Peter was called, oure Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyoure Ieſus Chryſte went into his houſe, and healed his wifes mother,<note place="margin">Math. viii.</note> whych was ſicke of an ague?<note place="margin">Iohn. xxi.</note> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, wente not Peter to hys olde occupation againe, after that Chriſt was riſen againe from death? where by it is eaſye to vnderſtande, that the Apoſtels dyd not ſo forſake all, that they had, but that it was lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for them to returne againe vnto theyr owne. Beſydes all thys,<note place="margin">i. Cor. ix.</note> it is playnely wrytten, that bothe Peter, and other of the Apoſtels dyd carye about theyr owne wiues, when they trauayled among forrayne &amp; ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge nacyons, preachynge the Goſpell of our ſauioure Ieſu Chriſt. Whereby it is euydente and playne that they forſoke them not vtterly. Fynally in this worde, all, there is a fygure to be vnderſtanded,<note place="margin">Synecdoch and what it is.</note> which is called Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necdoch, wherby other whilles, part is taken for the hole, and the hole for parte. Therefore, when it is ſayde, that the Apoſtels forſoke all, it is to be vnderſtanded of thoſe thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it
<pb facs="tcp:6563:72"/> is lawfull for a man to forſake: But it is ſo farre of, that the Chryſtyan relygion ſhould conſtrein or compel any man to forſake his wyfe and his chyldren (excepte it be in an vrgente neceſſitie, as when we muſte ſuffer for the word ſake) that rather it doth call them all infydelles and worſe than infidelles that doe not prouyde and ſee to theyr owne houſeholde,<note place="margin">i. Timo. v.</note> of the whych houſehold, ye wil graunt me, that the wyfe and chyldren are the chiefeſt part. Why doeth not the ſayng of Gregory take place among them where he ſaith:<note place="margin">Grego. 27. queſt. 2. cap. Sunt qui</note> ſome do thinke that for religion ſake, mariage ſhuld be diſolued and broken, but we muſt conſider, that thoughe mans lawe doeth permitte it, yet gods law hath forbydden it. For, the trueth hym ſelfe doeth ſaye: Whome god hathe coupled together,<note place="margin">Math. xix.</note> let no man put a ſunder. Agayne: Let no man put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye hys wyfe, excepte it be for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication. Who will wythſtande the maker of ſo ſtrong a lawe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:6563:72"/>
               <p>Gregory doth not ſpeake there of the Chriſtian religion, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
                  </label> but of mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerye, whyche they do commonlye terme, with this terme religion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>The true Chryſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Very well,<note place="margin">Monkery among the papiſtes, is of more perfecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on then chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes religion is.</note> I am content that it be taken ſo: yet ſhall ye be fayne to graunt, that monkerie is, after your doctrine, a more perfecte religion, then the religion of Chriſt is. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>upon I will make mine argument after this ſorte: It it be not lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to breake wedlocke for monkery ſake, whiche is of more perfection: howe much leſſe ſhall it be lawefull to breake matrimonye for chriſtian religion ſake, whiche is of leſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection? But ye ſaye, that it is Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories meaninge, that a man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man maye not breake wedlocke for to enter into monkerye, muche leſſe then ſhall it be lawfull for to breake matrimonye for chriſtian religion ſake, which as I ſayd, by your owne doctrine, and after the opinion of many men is of leſſe perfection than monkery is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:73"/>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ſayd, me thinke, that both Peter and alſo other of the apoſtelles dyd cary about their wiues with them, when they went about to preache. Where (I beſeche you) do ye fynde that written? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtin. </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chryſtian.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">i. Corinth. ix.</note>Thus is it wrytten, and thus do we read in the firſte epiſtell to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians: Haue we not power to eate and to drinke? Haue we not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to leade about a ſiſter to wife, (ſome do tranſlate theſe Greke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Adelphen Gyneca, a chriſtian wife) haue we not power, I ſaye, to leade aboute a ſiſter to wyfe,<note place="margin">Cephas is Peter.</note> as wel as other apoſtels &amp; as the brethren of the lorde and Cephas?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Saynct Paule doth not there ſpeake of the apoſtelles wyues: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> but of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt chriſtian matornes, which folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the apoſtelles, whether ſo euer they went for to miniſter vnto them in theyr neceſſities,<note place="margin">Max. xv.</note> As we read that certaine women, folowed our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6563:73"/> our Ieſu chriſte from Galilee, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring vnto him of their ſubſtaunce.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Without all doubt ſome expound it ſo, as ye ſaye. But I can not ſee, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere </seg>
                  </label> howe it ſhould ſtand with the truth. For firſt and formoſte, althoughe it was lawefull in the countreye of Iurye, that ſuche honeſte matrones ſhould folowe the prophetes and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtels, for to miniſter vnto them in theyr neceſſities, yet the ſame coulde not haue bene done among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then without verye great ſuſpicion. But this is moſt true that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelles did to the vttermoſte of theyr power auoyde and exchewe all ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and lewde ſuſpicions, leaſt they ſhould by any meanes geue an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that the goſpell of our ſauyoure Ieſu Chryſte ſhould be hindered. What ſhoulde haue bene ſayde, I pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y you, amonge the Gentiles, if ſuche luſtye yonge men as ſome of theym were, had gone aboute wyth other wyues ihen theyr owne?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:74"/>
               <p>It is to be beleued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they had theyr owne wiues with theym,<note place="margin">Matrimonye was alwaies in eſtimation and honour among the Gentiles.</note> ſith that they knewe, that euen amonge idolatrous Gentiles, matrimonye was alwayes had in greate reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and honour. Againe, if ſ. Paule did ſpeake of ſuche women as folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the Apoſtelles for to miniſter vnto theym in theyr neceſſities, he him ſelfe did great wronge vnto the churches of Macedonia and of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaia, whom he did robbe, takynge wages of theym,<note place="margin">ii. epiſt. to the Cor. xi. cha.</note> that ſo he mighte preache freelye vnto the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. For, ſuch honeſt women might haue miniſtred vnto him, aſwell as vnto other, all maner of thinges, that he ſhould haue neded, wythout puttinge of the churches of Achaia, and of Macedonia to ſuche intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble charges. Whereby it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that he did ſpeake of none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but of the apoſtelles wyues. For his meaninge was, that it was as lawefull for him as for the other apoſtels, to take a liuinge of theym vnto whom he did preache the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6563:74"/> not onely for him ſelfe, but alſo for his wife: whych thing neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he would not do, leaſt he ſhould be chargeable vnto them. Moreouer who hath power to leade anye other woman beſides his wife? The huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande hathe power onelye ouer his wife, and not vpon an other woman Sith then that ſainct Paule ſayeth, that the bretherne of the lorde, and Cephas (which is Peter) had power to leade women about, it is without all controuerſie, that he ſpake of none other but of theyr owne lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wiues.<note place="margin">Euſe. eccleſi. hiſt. lib. 3. cap. 3.</note> But ye ſhall heare what Clemens Alexandrinus dothe ſaye writing agaynſt them that dyd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne mariage: Do they (ſayeth he) diſalowe the Apoſtelles? For, both Peter and Philip had wiues, and gaue theyr doughters vnto huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. And a litel after it focoweth.<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> They reporte (ſayeth he,) that when Peter did ſee, that his wife was led away for to ſuffer, he did reioyce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the election. And that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he did crie out aloude vnto her,
<pb facs="tcp:6563:75"/> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe was led forth, &amp; calling her by her name did ſay. O wife remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber the lord. Nowe do ye ſe plainely, that neither Philip, who was bothe a deacon, and a preacher of the ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell, nor yet Peter, whom ye wyll haue to be chiefe among the apoſtels did put awaye there wiues, till the lorde who had coupled them, did put them aſunder. I may then conclude and ſaye,<note place="margin">Concluſyon.</note> that we haue ſufficient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples bothe in the olde and newe Teſtamente, that pryeſtes whyche wante the gifte of chaſtitye, oughte to marrye, and haue wiues of theyr owne, that they may kepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues vndefiled members of our ſauioure Ieſu Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Howe be ye able to proue, that after they were ones called,<note place="margin">A foolyſh ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, howe be it the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſtes be not aſhamed to vſe il.</note> they did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with theyr wiues after the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of the worlde, thoughe they had them wyth them, whether ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they went?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:6563:75"/>
               <p>In good ſooth, neyghbour, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere </seg>
                  </label> neither ye nor al the prating papyſtes, were euer pillowes or boiſters vnto them for ro teſtifye of the ſame, therefore leauing ſuche ſubtell queſtions vnto them that lyſt to buſy theyr braynes about ſuche vanities, we will proue by playne and manifeſt ſcriptures, that all prieſtes whiche haue not the gift of chaſtitye, ought to marye. Fyrſt and formoſte theſe be the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the bleſſed Apoſtell Sayncte Paule:<note place="margin">i. Corin. vii.</note> For auoydinge of fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let euerye man haue his wyfe, and euery woman her huſbande. In this generall or vniuerſall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,<note place="margin">They are I warrant you euerye enche of them.</note> Sayncte Paule doth compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all men, as well pryeſtes as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, excepte ye wyll ſaye that prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes are no men. Therfore they are as well as all other men, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by Paule to haue wyues of theyr owne,<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> except they be made chaſte from aboue. Agayne: they that can not abſteyne, let theym marrye. Here doeth the Apoſtell, geue generally a commaundemente
<pb facs="tcp:6563:76"/> vnto all them that can not abſteyne that they ſhould marye, he excepteth none. Therfore they that forbid ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage vnto anye perſone vppon the earth, whych can not liue wythoute it, are felowes of them, or rather the ſelfe ſame, that ſayncte Paule doth prophecie of,<note place="margin">i. Timo. iiii.</note> ſayenge: The ſpiryte ſpeaketh euidently, that in the later times, ſome ſhall departe from the fayth, and ſhall geue hede vnto ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of erroure, and deuelliſhe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of theym,<note place="margin">A conſcience marked wyth an hot yron, is an vnclene conſcience de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, marked, and prynted with many markes of worldelye luſtes.</note> that ſpeake falſe by hipocriſie. And haue theyr conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences marked with a hot yron, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddinge to marrye, and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to abſteine from meates which god hath created to be receiued with thankes geuing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>But once preachers do ſaye, that ſaynct paule doth here prophecie of certaine heretikes, which afterwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des did moſt falſely affirme that ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riage was inſtituted and inuented of the Deuell. Suche were Tatius, Martion, and Manicheus, of whom
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6563:76"/> ſaynct Auguſtine doth ſpeake in his booke of hereſies.<note place="margin">Augu. in lib. heretico.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe heretikes did forbid mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in general, but your holy father the pope doth forbydde it in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare. Agayne there be certaine times in the yeare, when by his lawes no man may marry.<note place="margin">Tatius, Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and Manicheus enemyes of matrimony.</note> Is not this to be a companyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Tatius, Martion, and Manicheus, I ſay, that the pope can not excuſe him ſelfe, but that he is a Tatianiſte, Martioniſte, and a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichean, and euen of the number of thoſe heretikes that ſaincte Paule doth ſpeake of there in the ſentence afore alleadged.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>The churche doth not forbyd mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, but it hath onely ordeyned, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> that they whiche will be made pryeſtes, ſhould binde theym ſelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s by a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne vowe, to kepe perpetuall cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Is not the one as euell as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> For it belongeth not to the
<pb facs="tcp:6563:77"/> Church to requyre any ſuche thinge of the prieſtes. It is oure Sauyoure Ieſus chriſte onely, who is the onely Maſter and heade of his congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and church, to whom ſuch autori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie doth pertaine: As for the autority of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church it is limited by his word and can extende no farther, than the word wyl permitte or ſuffer. In the meane while both the pope &amp; all hys adherentes which either forbyd ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryage to them ſelues or to any other are plaine Tatianiſtes Manicheans and Martioniſtes.<note place="margin">The Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chians.</note> As farre, as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, there was a certaine kinde of heretikes, whych were called Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachians, which dyd ſo abhorre ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in the Miniſters of the church, that they wolde in no wyſe receaue the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Oute of the counſel of Gangris.</note> at the hands of them that had wiues. And againſte them was a godly decree made, in a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell that was holden at Gangris in the contrey of Paphlagonia. Thys is the very decre it ſelfe: He that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a difference of maried pryeſt as thoughe by reaſon of maryage, he
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6563:77"/> oughte not to offer or to miniſter the communion,<note place="margin">They that abſteine form the communy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of a maried pryeſt, are pronounced accurſed.</note> &amp; doeth alredy abſteine from his oblation, let hym be accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they not then all by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this decree excommunycated and accurſed that holde opynyon, that maryed pryeſtes maye not my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in the Churche of Chryſte? Though they be abomynable whore mongers, adulterers, drunkardes,<note place="margin">Meete cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions to ſerue lady Miſſa.</note> blaſphemous ſwearers fighters and blaſers: yet they wyll finde no faute wyth theyr oblation: Yf they doe but once ringe the belles, to theyr diuine and holye ſeruyce, they wyll flocke vnto them as the ſheepe doe to the folde. But if they doe heare of a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed myniſter, though he be neuer ſo well learned, thoughe all hys ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye is to ſet forthe purely and ſincere lye gods holie and ſacred worde,<note place="margin">Nothynge can ſet forthe the Pope ſhauelynges but feygned chaſtytie.</note> and to mynyſter moſte ryghtelye the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes accordynge to the lordes inſtytution &amp; ordeynaunce, thoughe his conuerſation and liuing be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether angelical, that is to ſay, moſt
<pb facs="tcp:6563:78"/> godlye and vertuous: yet wyll oure pope Euſtachians deteſte &amp; abhorre to receiue the communion or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſacrament at his handes, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king moſt vngodly that the maryed miniſters of the church are more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed and polluted, by companienge wyth theyr owne lawefull wiues,<note place="margin">I my ſelfe haue hearde a great many ſaye ſo.</note> than if being vnmaried, they ſhould lye commonly with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon whores and harlots of the ſtewes. Yea, the popes ſhauelinges their ſelues, be not aſhamed to ſaye, that it is for them a leſſe offence before god, to lie with a hundreth harlottes, than to haue wiues of theyr owne.<note place="margin">A verye ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanciall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumente I aſſure you.</note> For, ſay they, if we haue neuer ſo many har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lottes and take oure pleaſure wyth them, whenſoeuer we lyſt, we maye repent the next day, and being ſhri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, we ſhall obteyne at oure holye father the popes handes (whiche is the vicare of god,<note place="margin">The Pope is the vicare of God.</note> here in earth, and hathe abſolute power to do what ſo euer he liſt) free remiſſion of our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes bothe <hi>a paena et culpa:</hi> But if we haue wyues of our owne, we ſhall
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6563:78"/> liue in continual vnclenelineſſe,<note place="margin">In deede good chriſtian reader they call matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye nothynge but vncleane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, &amp; pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that they call it a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is for none other thing but that they maye haue the handeling of it vnder theyr iuriſdiction, &amp; ia their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall court. Eſay. v.</note> and ſtinking pollution whereby it ſhall come to paſſe, that we ſhall neuer be pure and cleane, for to come to the altare of the lorde. Who would not iudge, I beſeche you, that ſuch vyle perſons are geuen ouer into a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſence, and that all godly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſtanding beinge by the righteous iudgement of god, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken awaye from theym, they do call that whiche is good euell, and that whiche is euell, good, they do call lighte, darkeneſſe, and darkeneſſe, lyghte, eſteminge that to be ſweete which is ſoure, and that whyche is ſoure, to be ſwete? In the ſixt ſinode or counſell that was holden &amp; kepte at Conſtantinople, where it was forbidden,<note place="margin">The ſixt Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node holden at Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</note> that no man ſhould take vppon him the vowe of ſingle life, and alſo commaunded that all they that for any eccleſiaſtical orders, did put away their wiues, ſhould be put from the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the faythful: this holy decree was made. If anye man preſume contrarye to the rules
<pb facs="tcp:6563:79"/> and Canons of the Apoſtels to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue anye pryeſtes or deacons,<note place="margin">Diſtinc. 31. canon. Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam in rom. ordine.</note> from the touchinge and communion or fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhyp of theyr lawfull wyues, let hym be depoſed. Againe, if any prieſt or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, doe for religion ſake, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel or put awaye hys wyfe, let hym be excommunycated, and if he perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in it, let hym be depoſed. Manye other Canons and decrees mighte I aleadge that doe pronounce them to be accurſed, that either forbid prieſts to marrye, or that goe aboute by vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent and tirannous lawes to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them that be alredye maryed in the lorde, from theyr lawful wyues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> Thoſe decrees and Canons haue bene abolyſhed by the latter Concil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, therefore they ſtand in no effect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> Howe ſhall then theyr doctrine ſtande, where they ſaye, that concels cannot erre? Yf the later concilles do abolyſhe the decrees and Canons of the olde auncyente Concilles, then they muſt nedes graunte, that they
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6563:79"/> dyd erre:<note place="margin">The canons and rules of the Apoſtels.</note> els they wold not abrogate and put downe the decrees and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons that haue bene made in them. But nowe wyl we come to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons and rulers of the Apoſtelles, whiche are ſet forthe vnto vs in the booke of god: A byſhop, ſaieth Saint Paule, muſte be blameleſſe, the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande of one wife,<note place="margin">i. Timo. iii</note> ſuche a one as ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth wel his owne houſe, and ſuch a one as hath hys children in ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with all reuerence. For if a man cannot rule hys owne houſe, howe ſhall he care for the congregation of chriſt? This ſhal ye haue in the third chapter of the Epiſtel to Timothee, which chapter I wold faine haue you to reade through for there ſhal ye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo find, that both miniſters and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons oughte to be huſbandes of one wyfe. And beſides that, what quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties their wiues ought to haue. The verye like ſhall ye haue in the fyrſte Chapyter of the Epyſtell to Titus. For,<note place="margin">Titus. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> there the Apoſtell wryteth on this maner: for this cauſe I left thee in Crete, that thou ſhouldeſt ordeine
<pb facs="tcp:6563:80"/> elders in euerye citye, as I had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted the.<note place="margin">Gala. i.</note> If anye be blameleſſe, the huſbande of one wife, hauinge faythfull children, whyche are not flaundered of riot, nor are diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. Theſe are the rules and canons of the holy apoſtelles (for hauing all one ſpirite, they did ſet forth all one doctrine) whereby the elders or prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of the chriſtian church may law fully marrye. And trulye, if an aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell from heauen, ſhould teache any other doctrine contrarye vnto them, I would coumpte him accurſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> But our preachers did ſaye, that it is not the apoſtelles meaninge, that a byſhoppe muſt of neceſſitye be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, or that he muſt be maried, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is in the office of a byſhop. For Paule him ſelfe, beinge a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent biſhop was not maryed, nor yet ſaynct Iohn the euangeliſt, with many other that had bene byſhops, but that rather none that had had many wiues ſhould be choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuch an excellent office. For ſo Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6563:80"/> Ambroſe, Hierome, and The<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ophylacte, do expound the wordes of the apoſtell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>When Creſconius Grammaticus did aleadge a certayne epiſtell of the bleſſed martir ſaynct Ciprian,<note place="margin">Aunſwere.</note> for to mainteine his opinion and doctrine agaynſt ſ. Auguſtine,<note place="margin">Augu. contra Creiconi. Gramaticum lib. 2. cap. 32.</note> this holye by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of God did aunſwre him thus I am not moued with the auctority of this epiſtell: for, I do not take the letters of Cipriane, as canonicall ſcriptures, but I am wonte to trye his letters by theym (meaninge the Canonicall ſcriptures) and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer in theym doth agree with the auctoritye of the canonicall ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, I do with his prayſe and than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes geuing receyue and embrace it, and whatſoeuer doth not agre with the auctoritye of theym, I do by his good leaue, vtterly reiect and refuſe it. Euen ſo nowe, will I aunſwere you touching Chriſoſtome, Ambroſe Hierome, and Theophilacte, I do not take their writinges as canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb facs="tcp:6563:81"/> ſcriptures vnto the which onely I do owe a conſent without any con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tradiction or gayneſayenge) but I do trye them by thoſe heauenly and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall ſcriptures, and whatſoeuer I no finde in theym to be grounded vpon the infallible worde of god, the ſame do I with all reuerence due vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to ſuch worthy men,<note place="margin">Aug. in epiſt. ad fortunati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo deo.</note> embrace and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue: but if I finde any thing in theyr writinges and workes, that doth diſagree from the trueth of the holy and ſacred ſcriptures, geuynge them ſtill the honour, that ſuch wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thye members of the churche do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, I do vtterly reiect and forſake it. Which thing I intende to do, in this text, that we haue now in hand For, by the leaue of holye Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and of theym all, S. Paule doth not meane in this place, that he whych hath bene the huſband of one wife,<note place="margin">The argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the papiſtes bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vpon theyr owne Heades.</note> ſhould be choſen to be a biſhop but rather he that is the huſband of one wyfe. For els it ſhould folowe, that he which hath bene blameleſſe, &amp; not whiche is blameleſſe, ought to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6563:81"/> be promoted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dignitie and office: ſo that it were enough for him, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they call to ſuch an highe rowme, if he hath bene blameleſſe, diligent, ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, diſcrete, a keper of hoſpitalitye, &amp;c. nor by their owne ſayeng, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſary, &amp; requiſite, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhuld be ſuch a one, neither whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is choſen, nor yet when he is in the office it ſelfe. For it ſhalbe enough, that he hathe bene ſuche a one alreadye. Trulye neighbour, the one doth ſtande with as good reaſon as the other. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I dare boldly ſay, that the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of the apoſtelles is, that a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, which hath not the gift of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie, oughte to be the huſbande of one wife,<note place="margin">Extripartita hiſtoria. li. 2. capi. 13. diſt. 31. canone ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cena.</note> that by his chaſte and holy conuerſacion or dwellinge with his lawefull yokefelowe &amp; wife (for Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phnutius did call it chaſtitie to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye with his owne wife onelye, whereunto agreeth Chriſoſtomes ſayeng,<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. ad populum An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiochenam.</note> the firſte degree of chaſtitye is virginitie, the ſeconde, faythfull matrimony). He ſhould be an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of like godlineſſe vnto al the hole flocke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:82"/>
               <speaker>Robyn Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> Doth not ſayncte Paule ſaye the like, of the widowe, whiche he will haue to be receyued vnto the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye of the church? For, there it is written (ſay they) on this maner.<note place="margin">i. Tim. v. Thys goodly texte did gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dener aleadge agaynſt me.</note> Let no widowe be choſen vnder thre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcore yeres olde, and ſuch a one as is the wife of one man. Yf ye wil haue this to be taken, as it is wrytten, and admitte no expoſicion, how can ſhe be both a widowe, and the wyfe of one man. As then the bleſſed apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtel ſaynct Paule muſt be vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this place, ſo muſt he be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded in the other textes that haue bene aleadged before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Criſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> This I ſaye, that theſe Antichriſtes ſhall make an aunſwere before the iudgement ſeat of almighty god, for falſifyenge and wraſtinge his holye and ſacred ſcriptures. This is the very texte: Let no widowe be choſen vnder three ſcore yeares olde, and ſuche a one as was the wife of one man, whiche tranſlation doth agree
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6563:82"/> both with the Greeke and the latine But they are aſhamed of nothynge: they haue put on whores faces.<note place="margin">The papiſtes haue put on whores faces</note> So that they may by hooke or by crooke maynteyne their kingdome (whych is altogither leaſing and falſehode) they care not what they prate or ſay. Be it right wronge, it ſhall out, and all for to daſell the eyes of the ſimple ond ignoraunt people. But the moſt righteous lorde, will not alwayes wincke at their wickedneſſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godlye doinges,<note place="margin">ii. Theſſo. iii.</note> but will (when he ſeeth his time) wake oute of ſleepe, and wyth the breath of his mouthe ourthrowe their tirannous and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godly kingdome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>There be ſome,<note place="margin">A ſubſtantial expoſition, and worthy to be written in god bachus booke.</note> that by the ſame one wife, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the biſhop or prieſt ſhold haue, do vnderſtand one benefice. As though Paule ſhould ſaye. The byſhoppe or prieſt muſte be contente witho one benefice. Theſe do vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dand by the biſhops or prieſtes houſe nothinge els but the churche and by their children, thoſe that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb facs="tcp:6563:83"/> vnto their charge. Some a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine do ſay that pauls meaning is, that they oughte to haue none other wyues but the Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">Gaye ſyrs I tel you, for to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the church.</note>How doth it chaunce then, that they ſay, that they be maried vnto our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die? The holy ſcriptures doe teſtyfye vnto vs, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only chriſt is the huſband of the church. Therfore, ſhe wyll ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer acknowledge ſuch wilde &amp; luſtye ſtalantes, or rather ſtincking goates for her huſbands. Againe, yf Sainct Paule doth meane by theſe wordes, let the biſhop or prieſt be the huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of one wife, that they oughte to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent them ſelfes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one benefice: how doth it come to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome of them haue ſo many benefices, that they do ſcarcely know the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of them? Is this to kepe the Canons &amp; rulers of the apoſtels? Moreouer where they ſay,<note place="margin">We wil kepe them, as long as it is for our profyte</note> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> by the biſhop or prieſts houſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, &amp; nothing els is vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded it is a plaine &amp; manyfeſt lye, as anye man that doeth but onelye reade the texte, ſhall eaſelye perceaue.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:6563:83"/>
               <p>The wordes are theſe:<note place="margin">i. Timo. iii.</note> If a man can not rule his owne houſe, howe ſhall he care for the congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſt? Meaning thereby, that if a man can not rule his owne houſhold, or bring vp his youth godlye and in the feare of god, he is not worthy to be put in truſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the church &amp; congregation of Chriſt. Ponder and weygh the texte diligentlye your ſelfe, and ye ſhall finde, that it is none otherwiſe than I ſaye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Is this worde oportet, or muſt, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> of ſuch importaunce, that generally all biſhops and prieſtes muſt mary and haue wiues?<note place="margin">This queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo, did Gardener aſke me.</note> Howe doth it happen then, that Latimer, Doctour Ridley biſhop of London, and doctour Tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour biſhop of Lincolne, wyth many other, which I could reherce, whom ye do recken al to be honeſt and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men had no wiues?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>It is of ſuch importaunce, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere </seg>
                  </label> that by it all Byſhoppes and prieſtes, that haue not the gifte of conſtinencie,
<pb facs="tcp:6563:84"/> or chaſtitie, are bound to marye, and haue wyues of theyr owne:<note place="margin">Wolde God this were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued and kepte in all places.</note> in ſo much that if there were any biſhops or prieſtes, that hauing not the gift of continencie would not mary, the magiſtrates (if there were anye god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines or feare of god in their hearts) ought to compell them to mary, and if they will not obey, to depoſe them leaſt by proceſſe of time, they ſhould fall into whoredome, and ſo be an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſlaunder to the churche. As for thoſe bleſſed martirs of GOd maiſter doctour Hugh Latimer, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerende father mayſter doctour Rid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ley, moſt worthy byſhop of London: all their aduerſaries can ſay none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. but that they had a moſt ſpecial gifte of chaſtitye, whyche they did ſo declare in their liuing and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all the dayes of their life, that no man could euer laye anye thynge to their charge,<note place="margin">This can I iuſtyfye. For I haue heard them doe it.</note> touchinge that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and yet both they and alſo Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour Taylour, with many other mo whyche were gelded or made chaſte from aboue, did ſtoutelye defende al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6563:84"/> the maryages of prieſtes, &amp; of al other miniſters of the church of Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Yf ſo be that al they, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> that haue not the gifte of chaſtytye or continencye are bound to mary: How doeth thys come to paſſe, that Sainct Paule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge tempted with the intemperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the fleſhe did not marry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Bothe Ignatius,<note place="margin">Aunſwere. Euſ. eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticae hiſtoria li. iii. cap. xxx</note> and alſo Clemens Alexandrinus, whyche were verye nighe the Apoſtelles time, do plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye teſtifie that Sainct Paule had a wife. But let vs graunte that he had neuer none, where doe ye reade in al the newe Teſtament, that Saincte Paule was tempted with the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencie of the fleſhe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe be his wordes: There was geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me vnquietneſſe through the fleſh, euen the meſſenger of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than to buffet me.<note place="margin">ii. Corin. xii.</note> What ſhould we vnderſtande and by this, but the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy luſtes &amp; inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynency of the fleſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6563:85"/>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Howe ſaynte Paule ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded in the place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aleaged.</note>There Sainct Paule vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no ſuche thinge, but by the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe of the fleſhe, and meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Sathan, he doeth vnderſtande the perſecutions and troubles, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che by the ſtirringe and meanes of Sathan, he was faine to ſuffer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallye, for the Ghoſpell ſake, not onelye of the open enemyes, but alſo of the falſe bretherne. In ſo muche that ſome tymes, he ſemed to be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlye forſaken and geuen ouer of god, and that he was the moſt wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched &amp; myſerable man in the world. For, why? all the world was againſt hym. He coulde not come ſo ſoone in to a towne, but that he was by and by after, with knockes, driuen out of it: Seing him ſelfe manye tymes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied, euen of thoſe, that he did truſt beſte: Was not thys, thinke ye, a greate temptation to the fleaſhe? Therfore, did he many times, praye vnto the lorde, that he wolde deliuer him out thoſe afflictions &amp; troubles, whyche hys fleaſhe, dyd grudge to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6563:85"/> beare. Thus doth Theodoretus,<note place="margin">Theodore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Ambro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius and Era<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſimus in .xii. capitu. ii. ad Corinth.</note> Ambroſe, and alſo Eraſmus expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Ye did ſay a while ago, that neither faſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, nor beating of the body could quenche nor put out in man the fyer of incontinencie, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> excepte god did put it out bi his ſpecial grace. Why doth then ſaynct Paule ſaye,<note place="margin">i. Corin. ix.</note> that he dyd ſubdue and bryng his body vnder? For our preachers do vnderſtand by it, that ſaynct Paule dyd mortify in him ſelfe, the fyer of incontinencye, by longe faſtyng, by putting muche water into his wine, and by beating and ſcourging of his bodye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>Although ſayncte Paule had not had the gyfte of continencie or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie, yet neded he no long faſtinge: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">If our fat red cheke prieſts were but halfe handled as paule was they woulde not be ſo luſty as they are.</note> for manye times beynge ſhut vp in darke priſons he had nothing to eat. He neded not to put much water in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his wyne: For he dranke nothing elles but pure water, for the moſte
<pb facs="tcp:6563:86"/> parte. And what neede (I praye you) had he, to beate and ſcourge his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye? Dyd not he ſuffer ſtrypes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of the enemies of the trueth? And that he had the gyft of continen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie, it appeareth moſt manifeſtly by his owne wordes, whyche he dothe ſpeake in the fyrſt epiſtell to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians: I would (ſayeth he) that al men were, as I my ſelfe am. But euerye man hath his propre gyfte of God, one after this maner and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after that. Elles without all doubt, he would haue vſed the ſame remedye, that he did preſcribe, and offer vnto other. He did then by theſe wordes, meane and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that he did ſubdue and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye his body<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii. What ſainct Paule dyd meane in the ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aleaged.</note> for to liue accordinge to the doctrine that he him ſelfe dyd teache: &amp; that in all thinges he gaue a good example to the whole worlde For ye muſt vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beſides the incontine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of the fleſhe, there be in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many other concupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces which do moue a man to offend the lord. Theſe concupiſcences oughte to be
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6563:86"/> mortifyed by ſuche meanes, as God hath appoynted. Which thing ſaint Paule folowed, in mortifiyng them that were in his body. As for the fier of incontinency, it was all together quenched and mortified in hym. As we do learne euery where, bothe by hys owne wordes, and alſo by hys owne doinges. For as I ſaid before, if he had wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the gift of continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie or chaſtity, he wold wyth al than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes geuing, and ſubmiſſion of heart haue vſed the remedye, that he wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all other men to vſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>Are all the Chriſtians prieſtes? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
                  </label> for me thinke, that I hearde you ſaye of late that they were all pryeſtes. And this dyd I not onelye heare of you, but of manye other beſydes. I haue muſed many tymes, how that could be. Therfore, I wil deſyre you, afore we departe, that I may heare what is your aduiſe in it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>If ye do vnderſtande by the prieſtes, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> ſuche as be anoynted of God, for to
<pb facs="tcp:6563:87"/> offer ſacrifices vnto hym. I ſay that all Chriſtians are pryeſtes.<note place="margin">All chriſtians are pryeſtes and how.</note> For they are anoynted of god not wyth mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall or earthly oyle where wyth the body onely can be anointed but with the vertue of his holy ſpirite, whiche of the bleſſed euangeliſt ſaint Iohn, is called anointyng.<note place="margin">i. Iohn .v.</note> The lorde then anointing all Chriſtians, with this ſpiritual vnction or anointinge, dyd ordeine &amp; make them all, a ſpirituall or kinglye prieſthode,<note place="margin">What ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices the pryeſtes of the newe teſtamente do offer.</note> not for to offer brute beaſtes, as the pryeſtes of the old law did, but for to offer ſpirituall ſacrifices, I meane, the mortyfiynge of theyr owne bodyes, whyche is a liuely ſacrifice, holy &amp; acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, for to offer alſo, the ſacrifice of righteouſnes,<note place="margin">Roma. xii.</note> of prayſe, &amp; of than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes geuing with a contrite and hum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble hearte whyche are the true ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyces of all them,<note place="margin">Pſal. iiii. Pſal. l. Hebru. xiii. Pſalm. l.</note> that doe ſincerelye profeſſe Chryſte, and are denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or called chryſtians of hym. But yf by prieſtes ye doe vnderſtande the miniſters of the churche, I ſaye, that in the ſame ſignification, al Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6563:87"/> be not pryeſtes: for,<note place="margin">If by prieſtes we do vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians be not pryeſtes. i. Corin. xiiii.</note> they be not all called to the minyſtration of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Sacramentes, nor yet to the preaching of the goſpel of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſu chriſt. For in the churche all thinges muſt be done in order.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>And ought not the miniſters of the church to be anoynted after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the olde lawe? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The true Chriſtian.</speaker>
               <p>No, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere </seg>
                  </label> for after that Chriſt hath wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with his moſt precious bloud the conſciences of the chriſtians, all ſuch vnctions &amp; anointinges are vtterlye ceſſed, and are no more neceſſarye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong chriſtians: And al they that go aboute to brynge in againe, or haue brought in agayne alredye, into the church, ſuch Iuyſhe vnctions and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointinges, are falſe Prophetes. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom, S. paule hath written very ſharply in all his epiſtels, &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> epiſtel to the Romains, to the Galatians, and to the Hebrues. In dede the Chryſtyan Churche, doth vſe certayne ceremonyes, as is
<pb facs="tcp:6563:88"/> the triyng and examynyng of them whom they doe chuſe vnto that wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy office,<note place="margin">What cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, the churche doeth vſe in choſing or makyng of mynyſters.</note> where vnto is added th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> layinge on of handes. Of theſe cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monyes doeth Sainte Paule ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his Epyſtels, but ſpeciallye in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Epyſtel to Timothee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Robyn Papyſt.</speaker>
               <p>This then haue I learned in our<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> communication. Fyrſte that all the ſcriptures, whych our preachers doe aleadge,<note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Epito<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gus.</note> for to impugne and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the maryage of pryeſtes, are ſhamefully wrythed and wraſted.</p>
               <p>Secondlye, ye haue proued vnto me, that the vowes, whyches all relygy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons or ſeculare prieſtes, dyd make, for to bynde them ſelues per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually vnto the ſtate of ſingle lyfe, are directly againſte the holy and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſcriptures, and worde of God, and that therefore they maye lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully breake them, couplynge them ſelues in honeſt Matrinony, that ſo lyuinge in the feare of god they may kepe them ſelues vndefyled mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of oure Sauiour Ieſu Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:6563:88"/>
               <p>Thyrdlye, ye haue ſhewed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lared moſte manifeſtly, both by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xamples of the ſcriptures, and alſo by ſtronge argumente taken oute of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſame, that all religious perſons, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſecular pryeſtes, that haue not the gyfte of chaſtytye, ought to mary, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o much that if there were any, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he hauynge not the gyfte of chaſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye, wolde not marrye, the godlye Magyſtrates ought to compel them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd yf they bee dyſobedyente, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or put them downe, leſt by proceſſe of tyme they ſhoulde become an open ſklaunder vnto the churche. Now fare ye well in the Lord til another tyme.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
